All right, welcome back everyone. I hope
lunch was okay. Sorry if you had an
issue getting food. I know the lines
were a bit crazy out there. Um, first up
we have Peter Stone with Sony AI in UT
Austin. Welcome, Peter.
All right, thanks for the introduction.
Thanks all for being here. Um, so as I
said, I am coming from from UT Austin
and Sony AI. I'm going to talk mainly
about a recent result from Sony AI um on
um the first robot that can beat prof a
professional athlete at their own sport.
So I'll talk about that mainly, but
first I'll tell you I am coming from
from UT Austin um in two weeks. I'm
going to be the head of a new school of
computing there that brings together
three different departments. I was the
founding director of Texas Robotics.
We're going to be hosting the conference
on robot learning um this fall in
November. I hope to see many of you
there. And if you come, you'll get a
chance to see our beautiful new robotics
facility um and his gym. It used to be
the women's gymnasium when there was
such a thing as women gymnasia, but now
it's filled with robots. We also have a
machine learning laboratory. I'm deeply
involved in a in a ethical AI initiative
called good systems. And I'm really
proud of the AI education that we've
been doing there, including um a
publicly available, anybody can use uh
full course on AI literacy, essentials
of AI for life and society that's for
non- majors or anybody really, and also
an online masters for $10,000.
Um my research is is fairly broad, but
the um the question that unites sort of
all the things I've done over the years
is this one. to what degree can
autonomous intelligent agents learn in
the presence of teammates and/or
adversaries in real-time dynamic
domains? So, my group publishes in sort
of this the sub areas of um AI shown
here, especially multi-agent systems,
robotics, and reinforcement learning.
And some of the applications domains
that I' that I've used over the years
have been uh things like robot soccer.
So, you know, here's a a um video from
many years ago. Uh our team was the one
with their hands behind their the arms
behind their back. Um, we ended up
winning this competition with the uh the
now robots where you have to remember
these robots are fully autonomous. The
goal of Robocop is by the year 2050 to
have a team of humanoid robots that can
beat the best World Cup team on a real
soccer field. We're not quite there yet,
but things have advanced since that
video just uh a month a month ago. Um,
our team is shown in blue here. Um,
these are sort of bigger and faster
humanoid robots. These are made by
company called Booster. It's a beautiful
robot. But then we did all the
programming and it's a learned skill
here of walking and kicking using
reinforcement learning um and uh gotten
to the point where we can now um do
human put it makes sense to put humans
and robots on the same field. So here's
a clip where I take the ball um and
leave the ball for the robot and see
what happens. The robot's able to turn
and uh and score a goal. So um I also
work on general purpose service robots.
So uh things like this at Robocup.
There's also a competition called
Robocup at home where a robot has to do
things like putting away uh groceries,
setting the table, um interacting with
uh with with visitors. Um and so this is
a great domain for uh for general
purpose robots. And then prior to this
the table tennis result that I'm about
to talk to you about um my team at Sony
AI had a paper on the cover of Nature
about four years ago um where we were
the first AI agent to be able to beat um
the very best humans at a real-time
control task. In this case, Gran
Turismo. So in this video, the green
cars are trained with end-to-end
reinforcement learning. The white ones
are driven by some of the best uh
drivers in the world at Gran Turismo. We
outperformed them and that was featured
in in Nature. Um and now I also you know
work on uh also navigation not just in
road settings but in more social
settings. This is joint work with with
Jody Biswas where we have robots
navigating through the sort of hike and
bike trails through Austin um having to
not navigate uh social situations.
But the title of my talk and the main
thing I'm going to tell you about is a
result uh called ACE with my my team at
uh at Sony AI. Oh, one other thing I
wanted to tell you about because we just
publicized it a couple days ago is a um
a data set that we're collecting called
uh oopsy data which is about um robot
failures. So most data sets are about
robots doing successful things. This is
a community sort of a community sourced
effort to try to gather uh failure data
from robots and we hope that many of you
will contribute to this. So so look it
up. There's a way to contribute and
annotate what the failures were. um
postto talk in my lab Klaus Vulkar has
been been uh leading that
but the main topic of this talk is the
um a group this uh trying to um create a
table tennis player with this group at
Sony AI of course it's not just my work
uh it's a large team it was led by Peter
Dur he's really desire deserves the line
share of the credit here but a huge team
um effort it was featured on the cover
of Nature on in April 23rd so just three
months ago or
Um, and so you can read all about it
there and and get all the details. But
the motivation here is that games have
been a a benchmark for AI for for many
years in sort of turntaking settings um
like chess and go and poker um and then
some more real-time settings as I said
oops GT Sophie um was the first uh
real-time control task where we where um
humans did better the first real world
um outperforming um the the best humans
was drone racing. That was Dvita
Scaramutza's lab that was also featured
on the uh I think a cover of nature. Um
but that was not in a sort of
competitive head-to-head setting. Um
meanwhile, table tennis is sort of
one-on-one adversarial and has been used
as a motiv oops a motivator uh for
robotics research for many years. um uh
going back to the mid1 1980s. This is a
video from uh Google and Vincent who's
the next speaker played a role in this
one where a robot was sort of uh playing
very well in a cooperative kind of
setting. But there had been no example
of a of a competitive robot that's able
to beat um expert level players um using
Olympic rules. And so in this video I'm
going to show you the robot. Our robot
on the right is playing against a a
woman who has won twice won an Olympic
silver medal. She was once ranked fifth
in the world. Um I think at the time we
played her it was she was ranked 11th in
the world something like that. Um and
the robot is playing according to uh
professional regulations. So the the the
players area is the same. The robot has
to serve the ball um which has not
always been the case in in systems. So
it has a a cup where it can toss the
ball up and and uh and serve it. Um and
uh so I'm not going to be able to have
you know go through all the details here
but the general system setup is that
there's it's uh obviously it's not a
humanoid robot and it's uh you know so
the form factor is is um that we
actually built the robot custommade and
engineered it to be as light as
possible. It has to be able to move 20
meters per hit the ball 20 meters per
second every 8/10 of a second. That's to
get to professional level play. Um the
the cameras are all around the system.
There's nine that are positioned to get
the XYZ coordinates of the ball and then
three that are event-based gaze control
cameras that can uh track the spin of
the ball, which I'll show you in a
minute. And this is an overhead view
where you see the player area and the
robot workspace. The only concession
that we make to this being a robot is
that we don't allow the player to cross
the net for safety reasons, but
otherwise it's effectively regulation
Olympic rules.
Um the robot learns to play in
simulation. So the three main
contributions in the in the nature
article are the perception system, the
reinforcement learning for control and
then the hardware of the robot itself.
The the main control problem for us was
figuring out as the ball is coming in,
how do you move the arm of the robot to
be able to hit the ball given a
particular target and spin that you want
to um that you want to realize. And we
call that a skill as opposed to tactics
which would be where do you want you
know choosing where do you want to hit
the ball or strategy which would be
longer term uh you know what do I want
to do you know from point to point or
even game to game. So the real the the
most of our RL is at this low-level
skill level. Um much of it in simulation
but where the data is it's a physics
informed simulator. Sorry I keep
jumping. The physics informed simulator
where there's data from the real world
that builds the noise model, the ball
distribution model and the physics
model. And then there's an actor critic
where it's asymmetric. There's a true
state given to the uh to the um uh
critic and a noisy state given to the
actor and then the actor is what runs in
the um in the real world. Um I won't go
into the one of the big uh sort of
technical things we needed to do is come
up with a an action space that the robot
could um could deal with. So uh you know
because the we have it's a six degree of
freedom arm on two degrees of freedom
for the base. Um and so there's a very
sort of um counterintuitive set of space
points that the endeector could get to
and we find a way to map that to a one
uh um a sort of a hyper cube such that
any point in that hyper cube is a
feasible. So we call this feasible
action for optimal control and then
there's a model model predictive
controller that controls the endeector
um to try to to get the target that is
chosen by the reinforcement learning
agent. So, this video will show you sort
of how the robot can react uh quickly.
Um I'm going to you're going to slow it
down and see as it hits the net. The
robot was trying to hit a forehand, but
then after it hits the ball hits the
net, it adjusts and then swings its arm
back the other way and is able to still
hit the ball back. So, here's it. Here
it's again in real time. Whoops. In real
time, you'll see how quickly um the
robot responds. And we have several
examples on our on the blog and on our
website showing um examples of the robot
responding to these net balls in real
time. I said there's the event-based
camera that's that's tracking the spin.
There's no artificial marker on the
ball. So, it's just using the the logo
that's there. So, here's um what that
event-based camera sees as the robot is
spinning. Um so, the the mirror shown
here on the left is tracking the where
the ball is in XYZ coordinates. And then
in real time we're able to um determine
this the speed and the spin of the ball
which is then given as input to the um
to the RL agent. This is a robot video
where you have to slow it down to be
able to watch it. Most robot videos you
see them sped up a lot. Um here's a nice
video from the um from the viewpoint of
the uh of the robot. It's a camera
mounted on the arm and again slowed
down. So you can see it's tracking the
the spin and speed of the ball and then
deciding um how it how it should hit it.
I said the other contribution here was
the robot itself. It's a custom uh
customuilt robot where we use an an
optimization process to sort of um take
away all of the the mass of the robot
that isn't needed for structural
stability and reduced it 5 kilograms
from the original design so that we
could achieve the high speeds at at uh
at high frequency where there's um six
revolute joints and two joints on the XY
plane on the on the base. And then
there's also a uh a serve library that's
done using an evolutionary process where
the um where we have to where we get a
diversity of serves so it's not
predictable to the player. Um and so you
know the and then the robot will pick
one of them to execute. Um but it's you
trying to find some that have backspin
force uh top spin different uh different
locations and all of those are trained
in a um to be able to sort of start off
the point before it moves to the uh to
the standard RL controller for most of
for the rest of the rally. Um just in
terms of results the the Nature article
has results up until December 2025 where
we were beating um where we were losing
sometimes but uh but beating some
university level players. The ones shown
in red are losses. The ones in green, we
won at least one game against them. If
there's a T in the top, that means
they're a professional level player. And
then recently, just a couple a month or
so ago, we released released a blog with
all the results from this past spring
where we did beat this a woman who was
ranked fifth in the world at one point,
a man who was ranked 99th in the world
at one point. So really beating
professional level players. Um, and then
this is just showing some of the data of
how fast the ball is being able to hit
both back in April 2025 and 2026. We're
hitting the ball slightly faster than
than professional humans. Not quite
putting enough as much spin as uh as uh
professional humans. And this is showing
just another match um against um the uh
he was I think ranked n 99th in the
world. male professionals hit the ball
harder than than uh the female
professionals. And uh but we're able to
beat him as well um even at the at
really uh fast speeds. And so um uh all
of these videos are available online. Um
and I'll just you know in summary in
this video which will be the last one I
show is the the um a warm-up video. It's
the first time this woman was this uh
professional woman was um playing with
the robot and uh so it's not trying to
beat her beat her. It's like sort of
this, you know, warm-up phase. Um, but
you'll see at the end of the point that
she's really having fun, is really
impressed and and enjoying herself. But
the summary here is that for the first
time, we've shown that AI agents can
reach expert level performance in tasks
that require fast real-time
decision-making in physical space.
There's still many open questions. Can
the robot beat the world champion? We
don't know. Can expert table tennis
players use these robots to improve
their game? We actually do have some
examples already of of professionals
getting ideas of shots that they
wouldn't have otherwise tried. Um, and
you know, could we do this with a
humanoid? I think we're still very far
from that. Um, but uh there's uh, you
know, like I said, lots more um,
information on this online. And there'll
also be a talk on the main stage at 310,
I believe. Mika Springer with is the
president of Sony AI. Uh, he has a
10-minute talk. He'll talk a little bit
about this and some of the other
projects at at Sony AI, including uh,
GT. So, more about GT Sophie, the the
highspeed racing agent. So, uh with
that, thank you for your attention. I'll
be around if there's any questions
afterwards.
All right. Thank you, Peter. Next up, we
have um Vincent Vanoke, and he is with
Whimo. All right, Vincent, you want to
come up?
Let's
make sure we got your slides going.
There we go. Cool.
>> And where's the uh that's the
>> the clicker right here. There you go.
>> Thank awesome. Um well, thanks for
having me. Um I hope that for this crowd
I don't need to introduce uh Whimo but
if you don't know who is an agentic AI
company because of course except our
agents are you know big beautiful hunks
of metals uh that are have four wheels
and are driving around in your
neighborhood. Um we have by now
thousands of agents operating in the
real world uh doing very long horizon
tasks uh with uh to completion uh and
serving real customers uh paid customers
completely autonomously. We're right now
in 11 cities but we have ambitions to
expand to many cities in the US and um
abroad as well. Um so it our goal really
is to provide autonomy at scale uh and
to become the world's most trusted
driver. I like to always show this
notion of trust as a central uh central
feature of the Whimo story because it's
not just about safety. It's about
consistency. It's about um
repeatability. It's about
predictability. a lot of the same
features that are factors in the trust
that we place in agentic agents uh in
general. Um if you're already tired of
my uh you know joking around about the
parallels between autonomous driving and
agentic AI uh I'm sorry I'm just getting
started. Um there is actually a lot of
parallels uh to be made between physical
AI on one end and aentic AI on the other
hand. Like if I talk to my roboticist
friends uh uh and they look at what's
happening in the world of agentic AI
today, they really look at it with a
smile because all of the hard problems
that we've been experiencing in the past
20 years in robotics are exemplified in
Agentic AI, right? It's really about how
do you build a system that has enough
affordances to do things that are
interesting in the real world but that
also you can trust, right? And that you
can that can evolve in the real world
doing real tasks safely and with uh with
a good stability and consistency. And
all of those problems were first really
exemplified in the physical AI world and
are now hitting the agentic AI world. So
I want to take a few lenses
uh to look at agentic AI from the
perspective of somebody who's been
looking at physical AI for a while and
one lens we can take is the lens of
industrial automation. Right? So
industrial automation is, you know,
traditionally the art and engineering
behind taking a whole bunch of
components that are all, you know,
mostly do their work but will
occasionally fail and stringing them
together like on an assembly line for
example in in and harness them to
provide very high levels of reliability,
safety, autonomy um uh over very long
time horizons and at scale, right? There
are lots of lessons that we can draw
from um uh industrial automation for
agentic. I'm just going to you know pick
one, right? One of the lessons that I've
seen in this space is that um it's all a
game of nines, right? At a certain
scale, you can get away with 99% uh
repeatability. As soon as you scale up,
you need to go to 99.9 or 99.999
and and and so on and so forth. Every
nine
typically means you need a different
solution. Every nine that you earn is
not earned by just improving your system
a little bit, getting a better model or
reducing the error rate. You have to
redesign your system for the level of
reliability um that you want. So another
angle that we can look at uh AI from the
perspective of physical AI is the angle
of autonomy. Right? So in autonomous
driving we have those five levels of
autonomy. uh you start from no
automation to driver assistance systems.
Uh Whimo operates at level four very
high automation. Um if you think about
coding agents or AI agents, there is
this kind of same gradation of you know
you write your code by hand all the way
to you just yolo it and uh just let the
agent write everything for you. U one of
the lessons from AV in that space is
that level three is a weird beast. Level
three is not a very pleasant place to
be, right? It's very bad for cognitive
load. It's very bad for safety. It's
very bad for productivity. And we've
seen this in agentic AI as well when
people started moving from, you know,
code completion to agents. And having
this kind of mixed scenario where
sometimes the human is in charge,
sometimes the agent is in charge and
this interface between the two is very
uncomfortable. The other thing that
we've learned in the AV space is that
level two and level four are very much
different beasts. So the the the s the
very different design decisions, very
different approaches and uh you can't
really just graduate your way from an
level two to level four. You have to
rethink your system uh dramatically. And
we're seeing that in aentic AI as well.
It's not the code compression systems
that you you used to use uh are not
exactly you know a simplified version of
the agentic systems that you use today.
Um another lens that we can take is more
of the dynamical systems perspective.
Right? So there's a lot of work that's
been going on in control theory in the
robotic space um where you study
essentially nonlinear dynamical systems
and uh genetic systems are essentially
extremely nonlinear dynamical systems.
Um so maybe a lot of the physical math
that goes on there is not translatable
but the concepts and the way of thinking
about it notions of observability,
controllability, stability,
realizability that last one is you know
can you actually do the task all of this
is actually a very relevant to to the
task.
One of the lessons in that space has
been and it's lesson that has been uh
you know sort of adopted by you know the
the the agentic AI world uh
from the from from the from the start is
that if you want to optimize for closed
loop behavior meaning if you want to
optimize for long horizon you need a
very different reward system than if
you're trying to optimize for open loop.
So in the robotic space, this is
something we call the dagger problem.
And there's many names for that in
different fields. It's the idea that if
you're trying to if you have a system
that is a multi-step system and you're
trying to minimize the error at every
step, you may end up in a place where
you end up making very correlated errors
and at the end of the day your system
ends up in a very different place than
uh where you want to take it. Right? So
optimizing one step up at a time hasn't
really worked. That's why we do long
horizon planning. That's why we do
reinforcement learning. That's why we
think of long horizon tasks with a
different objective functions. One of
the ways that we approach this problem
is by optimizing one step at a time, but
by imagining the future and by looking
at the long horizon and dreaming up what
the long horizon uh can would look like
if we took a specific action. That's
where basically world models are coming
into play. And so at Whimo, we've been
working on world modeling uh to optimize
our system for longer horizon planning.
Uh we have our own world model which
we've called the Whimo world model.
We're very very creative. Um and that
enables us to do evaluation and
simulation of uh of longer horizon
behavior for our system in in um in in
closed loop and uh and with very good
fidelity. So a few of the ingredients of
a world model are well first and
foremost realism is is a is a big part
of it. Uh the way we've approached it is
we started off from a very good video uh
generative model Gen3 the from Google
deep mind as you can see here it's it's
got some notion of physics but it's got
all the all the notions of physics it's
it it can handle you know Minecraft
physics as well as real world physics
but we really want our our our role
model to follow real world physics not
just video game physics um we also want
the model to uh handle sort of real
world uh generative uh visuals, not just
video game visuals. So, we've basically
taken the model and fine-tuned and
adapted it to the Whimo use cases. So,
in this case, you see we have all the
cameras that are on the Whimo car. You
have the LAR. We've uh grafted
LAR generative capabilities onto the
model as well. And we're able to this is
a you know 30 second roll out of a
completely imagined uh scene uh from
this world model.
Um another important factor in world
modeling is controllability. You want to
be able to imagine counterfactual
events. You want to dream up what is
possible if you take any action. And so
you don't necessarily want to follow
exactly what has happened in the real
world. For example, you want to change
instead of turning right, you want to
turn left or go straight and still have
the model render essentially something
very high fidelity. And so we're able to
generate, you know, imagine new
scenarios that are very uh that are very
realistic irrespective of the action
that we take. Um we also want to be able
to control different aspects of the
scene. So through language we can say
hey generate that scene in the morning
generate the same scene at night change
the the weather conditions
can have cloudy weather foggy weather
change the appearance of things change
the the the the general um conditions.
Um we want to be able also to very
finely control the scene uh at a at a
very fine grain. Imagine if you move a
car from one lane to the other what
would happen as a result. So we have uh
in the controls basically we can
condition the entire model on all the
cars, all the pedestrians, all the lane
geometry uh of the model. Um and then
the next stage is really about
generalization, right? If we only are
able to simulate the kind of data that
we see in the real world today, it has
some uh usefulness, but really having a
world model really shines when you're
able to go and extrapolate in scenarios
that you've never observed or that you
potentially never want to observe. Um so
we've never encountered an elephant on
the road and uh but we you know we would
love to be able to simulate different
you know animal encounters like this.
Um,
one funny aspect of this is that if you
do nothing and you just train the data
on Whimo data, Whimo has never seen an
elephant on the road. So you say, "Give
me an elephant," the model will give you
no elephant whatsoever. If you try to
tweak it to improve its generalization
and world knowledge capabilities, it
will try really hard to give you an
elephant, but kind of fail in funny
ways. you have a a truck elephant like
elephantl looking truck uh because it
knows about trucks very well and it has
some notion of an appearance of an
elephant but it couldn't quite you know
square the the two together. Um and then
if you do it right then you can actually
have a full-on elephant on the road and
the model really understand the
different things. And what's interesting
is that you know our LAR has never seen
an elephant but uh it's able to generate
very reasonable uh LAR renderings as
well. Um so we can simulate scenarios
like uh what happens if we drive through
a raging fire. Uh we have never
experienced that but this is not a
completely uh implausible scenario. Uh
we can simulate having snow on the
Golden Gate Bridge. Um we can simulate
having uh somebody in a costume walk by
us. So this is actually a very realistic
scenario. you know, every Halloween we
will see people in costume drive uh
walking around in various stages of
inebriation sometimes. Uh so we want to
really really you know zoom in on hey
this thing that you see on the road here
that's actually a human being that's a
very vulnerable person right and so we
want to make sure that our system
recognizes that this is something to pay
attention to and to drive safely around
not just a random moving blob that uh
that that that that moves on the street
right there is actually a very
significant amount of uh safety that is
that that really deres from us
understanding the semantics of the scene
and we need to basically able be able to
validate that.
Okay. So this is a you know I only have
15 minutes so this is a very high level
but you know I really want to stress
that there is some interesting
connections between physical AI and
agentic AI. I think physical AI is
agentic AI taken to you know a the next
frontier. lots of lessons that can be
learned from robotics, from automation,
from autonomy that can be applied to
non-physical agents as well. Um, world
modeling is a very interesting direction
in general. Uh, you know, I want to ask
the audience that is working on virtual
agents, what is your world model? Are do
you have a very good high fidelity
simulation of your environment? because
that's a key uh to being able to do long
horizon planning and uh building some
resilience and uh long long long range
autonomy into your system.
Uh with that, thank you.
>> All right. Thank you, Vincent. Next up
is one of our very own Trevor Daryl with
UC Berkeley.
>> Thank you very much.
That was uh Vincent's talk was the
perfect precursor to my talk as I don't
have to spend any time explaining to you
why I am interested in physical AI. Um
and I'm going to tell you today about
recent work at UC Berkeley. There you
go. Okay. Want to make sure they saw it
there. um on real world reasoning agents
and in particular uh agents that can
see, feel, and reason about the physical
world. I mean, we already have agent vis
agents that can see, but they actually
don't always see that well, right? If
you look at the visual encoders in
today's VLMs and agentic VLMs, they're
uh welld designigned for internet vision
tasks, but they're not always that well
designed for physical AI tasks or even
precise internet vision tasks. Like, you
know, you can take an image, put it in a
visual encoder, uh run it through an
LLM, and get a nice caption. You get
another image, uh run it through the
same architecture, and maybe get the
same caption. You probably didn't
realize those two images were actually
different. You but you got the same
caption out of these encoders. I mean,
do you realize these are different
images? It's actually hard to see and
you probably have to look back and you
have, you know, there's some small
details there
and you probably have to look back and
forth between the images to actually
notice the difference. And that's
exactly what we don't allow most u
visual encoder architectures and BLMs or
aentic AI systems to do. Um, so let's do
it. That's what we did. So we engineered
a new state uh a representation we call
a stateful visual encoder that's
specifically designed to look for small
differences or what we call state
changes in the world. Uh specifically in
images here, but it could generalize to
other signals as well. So here's a basic
uh visual encoder diagram. take an image
uh encode it or rush it through push it
through a number of layers to encode it
and then put it into an LLM. We make a
very simple modification so simple you'd
be surprised that it's novel of allowing
uh
cross um cross image weights in the
middle layers of the encoder uh to
specifically be tuned to detect changes
that are too small to normally be
encoded in the representation.
And with that, you actually can have a
change encoder give you a very detailed
caption, mention what's changed, or if
you need to see whether a little box has
been checked or not in a web interface.
It's it's much much easier to do this uh
without tremendous um brute force
attack. How do you build this general
idea? There are a lot of different
approaches. We compare them all in the
paper. I won't go into details and I'll
refer you to the paper. uh has
significant improvement in a variety of
real world tasks like medical image um
report generation or um image editing uh
control or geospatial image uh change
detection. Uh and we have lots of result
tables as you would expect in our
wonderful project page and paper. Uh
please check it out if you're interested
in that. Stateful visual encoders.
So that's the seeing. I want to broad
you know
explain the broadness of the interest
here. We go from seeing manipulation
touching and eventually reasoning.
We want to manipulate things in the real
world the way people can. Huge challenge
of physical AI right now. Robots
generally can't do these things. We want
to be able to screw a light bulb in and
have it turn on. And I'll show you our
work on this that's called T-Rex. This
is in collaboration with uh colleagues
at NVIDIA. Current foundation models are
amazing, right? They can uh they can
reason, they can plan, they can act, but
they're still not so good at reacting.
And tactile is still the under I think
underappreciated modality. Certainly a
lot of cl a lot of real robotists
roboticists know this but a lot of the
sort of AI roboticists think oh you can
scale your way out of it without
actually understanding dynamic forces in
the real world. I'm not sure that's
right. Um human intelligence is dual
process and we really need agentic
systems that are dual or triple process.
We need this idea of a slow fast
architecture. And so we've embodied all
of these ideas in our approach we call
T-Rex both a data set data collection
and an architecture that has uh
multi-process dual process architectures
has tactile sensing and reactivity and
it can learn both how to feel in the um
in the dextrous manipulation sensor in
for example a sharper hand which is what
we use when to change the forces based
on what it feels when to adjust the slip
to catch catch something that's about to
slip or put just enough pressure on to
um you know peel a card off of a deck.
This is our platform. Uh and here's uh
example of our performance. So you can
see we have um uh two sharp hands. We
have cameras mounted on the head and the
wrists. And you can see the readout of
the tactile sense sensors in the lower
right tile. Um, and we can do tasks that
previously were impossible for um for
previous approaches that didn't have
tactile reactive policies. Um, and uh,
for example, squeezing a toothpaste out
of a toothpaste tube. We did not
actually yet ask the robot to brush its
teeth. U, maybe next time. Here it has
to feel to to sort of separate the two
cups uh, out of uh, out of a stack. Here
it's actually feeling the tile to
actually recognize which of the three
types of tiles it is just by the feeling
of the of of the indentations on the
tile um in majong.
Uh and here it's able to uh grab a key
and insert it into a lock and twist the
lock.
I think this is a little bit overnamed.
It's not it's really just pipet
manipulation with liquid. Um, and it can
the our T-Rex model can squeeze the bulb
to push just the right amount of liquid
out of it. Here we can extract a card
out of a deck.
And I think finally we get Oh, screwing
a light bulb in, I think, is the final
example.
And it knows how to put enough pressure
on it to not crack the light bulb. Um,
and those eggs that I mentioned earlier
were all real eggs. They were not
hard-boiled eggs. So um if you're
interested in in this I encourage you to
uh look at our web page and paper uh and
importantly our data set which may be
one of the most important artifacts of
this project uh Berkeley project with
strong collaborators from NVIDIA.
Um last but not least I want to talk
about world motion models. How do we now
reason in 3D in a very abstract way? Um
we all know how to predict the the 4D
future. We can look at a look at the
world, look out at a car, see maybe, you
know, key features on the car's wheel
and we can imagine how those are going
to move in time. And now we can build
and we've seen earlier today amazing
world models that are generating p live
video pixels of like predict every pixel
in the future going forward. It's
wonderful. But if I just want to, you
know, maybe adjust something on that
wheel as it goes by or or tighten a bolt
on the on the wheel like a F1 pit
driver, a pit pit crew, I don't need to
predict what the trees are doing. I
don't even need to predict what much of
the car is doing. I want to predict the
affordance or the geometry or how that
wheel is moving over time. What is what
uh what was, what is, and what will be
across time. Um so this is our latest
work on world motion models where we
build a motion model of dynamic 3D world
trajectories.
It's actually a world motion model over
SE3 trajectories. It's poses for those
of you who are sort of geometry
literate. And so much of the physical
world can be abstracted as the motion of
of rigid frames uh uh evolving uh and
and ours is the first very general
framework for predicting and completing
um and eventually doing things like MPC
over this representation. So we have a a
general model where a we've tokenized
the six degree of freedom uh pose frame
um and have it stacked over time with
multiple different reference frames one
corresponding to all the different
objects or rigid portions of a body in
the scene. So this is a world model over
SE3 poses. We call it a world motion
model. Other than that, it's very
general and in many ways the same as a
pixel as a world model that generates
pixels. We train it by dnoising uh
sequences. Uh and we can run inference
um uh either to predict the future given
the past uh to predict the future
condition on act conditioned on actions
given the past um to inpaint or motion
plan uh or to retarget uh solve for
dynamics etc etc. And we have a very
efficient neural network architecture uh
sorry transformer-based architecture
that does this. I'm just going to show
you in my one minute left some demos um
where all of these are being modeled by
our world motion model and you can give
given text cause the uh robot to learn
motion trajectories to solve a certain
task either directly or using something
like motion uh motion predictive control
to u to solve the motion. Here's
examples with the uh ammono data set
where we have human object interaction
uh and we need to generate the motion of
a humanoid in order to um perform a
manipulation task on an object in the
world. Our model outperforms baselines
on that and similarly interacting with
the world with objects and hands. So
you've seen quite a diversity of
different projects. Uh this is world
motion models. It'll be on archive soon.
Uh, keep your eye out for that. And I
only showed you a few of the
applications. Others are hinted on the
bottom of the slide. Very general model,
very cool. That's all I wanted to cover
today. Give you a teaser on three great
projects at Bear that see, feel, and
reason in motion about the real world.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you, Trevor. Next up,
we have Manmoan Chunractor from UC San
Diego.
That's it. Make sure I hope you're all
set. Okay.
Hey everyone. Uh it's good to be back at
Berkeley. Um I'm going to be talking
about autonomous agents u and maybe a
little bit about humans too.
All right. So uh I think all of us here
will agree that physical AI lives in the
open world. We have endless edge cases
that arise after deployment and we have
teams that go into continuous discovery
and development loops to fix these edge
cases and all of these must be fixed
with traceable release evidence.
Now the physical world is also rapidly
be becoming exe executable, right? So we
have uh all of these CI/CD frameworks
that can continuously run loops. We have
agents that can deploy code. We have
simulations to bridge gaps to data. And
all of this points to a future of
self-improvement.
However, physical stacks are complex and
require real world experimentation,
right? and a lot of real world knowledge
uh human expertise is something that
lives beyond static data. It requires us
to have scientific ideas. It requires us
to have expert workflows and physical
interactions with systems. All of this
means that experimentation and discovery
is something that requires a lot of
compute, a lot of data and a lot of
human talent for us to run in physical
workflows.
So in the next few minutes I'm going to
be talking about making autonomy
autonomous in collaboration with humans
and how we can have discovery frameworks
that are grounded in execution. How we
can reflect human intent in agentic
workflows and hopefully sustain
participation in AI native economies.
All right. So let's take this example
scenario. Um suppose you have an
autonomous driving um team and you
observe that you have an issue with
perception for pedestrians that would go
to a simulation team who would need to
figure out a way to handle these. Maybe
pedestrians are thin structures and it
requires us to have better 3D
reconstruction. So we can the team can
come up with let's say gshian splatting
as uh or a new method for gshian
splatting that can then be validated on
real data and eventually they can write
a paper about it or publish a spec
sheet. Now what if I told you that this
whole process is something that is run
by a team of agents.
The only input that comes from the
developer in this case is to generate
ideas to improve 3DGS to work with
pedestrians for autonomous driving, test
it on a particular family of GPUs,
validate it on real benchmarks, compare
to baselines, and publish a paper.
So the team of agents here plays a set
of specific roles. In particular, they
produce research that is verifiable.
They deploy code that is executable.
They come up with ideas that are
grounded in the physical world and in
general follow a process of scientific
discovery that's traceable and
verifiable.
So let's look at how this works. You
have the input come in. The agents
define the task that must be solved. In
this case, Omnire, a framework from
Nvidia is something that they decide to
improve upon. They come up with
hypotheses for dimensions where
improvement is possible. Specialist
agents then launch a set of different
experiments. Uh all of these experiments
are evaluated that is they are validated
and falsified on an ELO rated
tournament. Eventually there's one idea
with the highest ELO rating that would
survive. This is a new method that comes
up in this case which has been
implemented on real GPU hardware. So the
gains are measurable. It is something
that can be evaluated on real benchmarks
and then a team of writer and reviewer
agents can come in and write a paper
about it.
So
how good is the system? Well, so we took
a few of these papers and we submitted
them to a CVPR26 workshop on physical AI
uh related topic and with permission of
the organizers. By the way, we're not
trying trying to game the system. But um
three out of four papers that we
submitted did get accepted. One of the
papers got high praise. The paper that
was rejected uh did have formatting
issues with the equations and all. So we
believe reviewer do uh in this case. But
overall this is not a system which is
just for ideiating and for writing
papers. It's a system which is
performing traceable and verifiable
scientific discovery.
So how does this work? Everything rests
on a verifiable substrate on top of
which we can work. We define a
contextfree grammar which allows us to
come up with ideas that are grounded. We
every candidate method is something that
mutates on top of a verified
reproduction. Right? So everything is
something that we can measure. It's
something that we can validate and
falsify.
Finally, every claim that is made by the
system is something that we can trace to
a real log or a real line of code, a
real GPU run.
So the central engine that drives all of
this is essentially this verifiable
substrate. And how do we go about
building this? Essentially, we reverse
engineer the process. So uh suppose we
have a knowledge repository. Suppose we
have papers. Can we then follow this
scientific process to come up with the
code that wrote this paper, right? So um
how does that work? Let's take this
example. We have a paper out here that
has never been publicly implemented. So
it's not like cloud or GPT knows about
this paper. We analyze the paper. We
come up, we determine what are the new
ideas, what are the factors that are
giving us improvements over baselines
and those are the things that are then
produced in the code for this paper. The
code is something that is physically
verified against real data. Improvements
are suggested for the code and this is
something that we can then validate on
real benchmarks by comparing to real
data. Right? So this then forms the
verifiable substrate on top of which
discovery can happen.
Now if we have a full-blown application
like autonomous driving then what would
be the execution loops that build these
verifiable substrates in that case?
Fortunately, over the years for
autonomous driving, we have been working
on many such agentic substrates that do
data analysis for us, that do
simulation, that do AI model training
and validation.
So, for example, given a bunch of
computer vision and machine learning
tools, we can have data agents that can
analyze all sorts of edge cases. Given
an input from the user, for example, get
a car to change lanes, cut in or cut
out, we can get the get our simulation
agents to reconstruct the 3D background
to reconstruct all the dynamic agents in
the scene, deploy diffusion models that
can come up with novel reactive
behaviors and challenging edge cases.
And finally, other diffusion models that
can do photorealistic rendering or our
development agents can take all the OD
specs. they can take all the data tools
that we have, the simulation tools that
we have and do AI model training and
validation.
So once we have these autonomous systems
that are driving autonomy, what does it
mean for the role of the human? And I
believe that will define new loops where
as data starts moving from static to
interactive. We'll start harnessing
tacet expertise which gives us a handle
on the lived experience that drives
mental models that allow us to reason
about not just how experts act but why
experts act. Intents from these mental
models then drive the world models that
do not now work with just aggregated
preferences but have traceable
contributions. The attribution
mechanisms that we have now will allow
for trusted trusted adoption which then
leads to continuous participation of
humans in the AI loop.
So how do we build these mental models?
Well, we have the execution and the
discovery pipelines that we talked
about. All traces from these discovery
pipelines are then ingested and with the
claim back verification methods that we
have, we can convert them into
evidences. These evidences are distilled
into beliefs and the usage of each
belief by the system is something that
comes with an attribution. This is
something that can be used for coding
tasks where we can solve more tasks
better. Importantly, we can also have
less user interventions, less memory
tokens, less tokens being consumed which
essentially points to better user and
system alignment. This is something that
can also be used for physical tasks like
gshian splatting etc that we are talking
about where we can get mental models to
adopt different personas. for example a
quality and a and a speed persona and
these are things that come out of the
discovery loop and we can have a
controllable steering of these
mechanisms. So to summarize, we have
talked about execution loops that are
built on data simulation and devops.
These are the verifiable substrates on
top of which discovery loops can happen
which have grounded ideation,
verification and traceability. And
finally, human participation through
intent loops that work with tacet
expertise, mental models, trusted
attribution, and eventually co-evolving
partnerships. Thank you everyone.
All right, thank you man moan. Next up
we have Ble Joe with UCLA and Coco
Robotics.
>> Yes. So we have a faculties um from UC
Berkeley, UC San Diego down UCA. How
about having a UC AI summit? Um so I'm a
social professor at the UCLA and I also
work with Koko Robotics. Uh today I
would like to share with you how we
think about scale up the sidewalk
autonomy with world models. Right. So
probably most of the people here are
familiar with autumn driving. So we have
a previous uh speaker talk about their
amazing research on the road autonomy.
Right. So we have this fullsize vehicles
running around uh the cities. Um but for
our urban environment um there are
another kind of autonomy here I call it
the sidewalk autonomy. So here is a
sidewalk robots is doing the u food
delivery task. So this is a robot from
Koko robotics. So Koko robotics is a
startup running this kind of last male
food delivery service. So we we have we
we have hundreds of robot running around
to fulfill this task and you can see
compared to the roadside autonomy this
sidewalk robot have to handle a lot of
challenging uh settings. Um let me show
you some of the videos like from the
first person view of the robot. Now you
can see here this sidewalk robots have
to really carefully navigate on the
sidewalk and avoid the collisions of
obstacles. Also the robot uh has to
handle all the weather condition and the
lighting condition.
Also on the sidewalk you know originally
designed for people right. So the robot
have to properly and socially compliant
um interact with dynamic agents such as
pedestrians and animals like dogs.
Right? So here's another videos I like a
lot. Then you can see here is a dog just
lying on the sidewalk and then the robot
have to navigate very carefully to avoid
stabbing on the tail of the dog and
achieving the the navigation task.
Right? So from those video you can see
the sidewalk conditions are very
challenging. Also the robots work in a
compute and uh um battery constraint
environment right. So we we only allowed
to use uh single RGB cameras to do the
navigation.
So uh in recent uh years um people
develop lot of AI models for the
sidewalk navigations. So basically that
imitation learnings to learn from the
human uh demonstrations. So many models
have been uh developed. My lab have
contribute some of the models. Other
labs also propose uh some great models.
Uh so those models are trained on the
video demonstrations that it can
generalize very well across different uh
conditions. Um but we have a challenge
here giving so many different AI like
sidework foundation models. How can we
benchmark those navigation models before
the real world uh deployment right? Um
so um we are building up the um
benchmark. So here is a benchmark we
built called the sidewalk bench. So we
we want to uh evaluate the navigation um
policies or models uh in simulations. So
here we utilize a media omniverse and
isoxaxing to build uh the simulation
environments. So we can evaluate uh
different model and then compare their
capabilities how they interact with
peoples how they avoid uh collisions.
Um but if you look closely and those
graphical simulation um built in this
graphical engines still lack the visual
realism right? So compared to the real
world deployment there's still a scene
to real gap. So we want to address this
scene to real gap uh to more fairly
evaluate the model capabilities. Uh so
our solution here is creating the world
simulations from the real world uh
videos. So we want to use real world
videos as a source code to build up this
uh EV evaluation benchmark. Uh so here
is a work we developed last year
published at the CVPR. It's called V2.
And so we can take a videos like walking
on the sidewalk. Then we can build u
gion splants uh reconstructions from the
videos and turn this splat into this uh
physical engines. Then we can have this
kind of a datadriven uh simulations.
Then we can train and also evaluate the
sidewalk robots uh in this kind of
datadriven simulation. Um so here this
demo video showing you the training
process. So we can train the agent with
reinforce learning and then after the
trainings then the model can zero short
transfer to real world because there is
no definitive no uh visual gap between
the training environment and the
deployment.
Uh so based on this gion plant
environments how we can evaluate all
those different uh sidewalk navigation
policies and see how this model handle
different uh cases.
Um but still there is a limitation for
this kind of a video reconstruction
because we can only reconstruct one
environment from one videos right so
ideally we want to create several
variations from the same uh videos. Um
so that's a motivation behind uh a
recent work we called urban versse. So
we want to create uh multiple digital
cousins from the single video right. So
here the digital twins means one video
correspond to one simulation
environment. Uh the digital cousins
means we can have a different
variations. So here we utilize the
computer vision techniques to extract
the scene graph from the input videos.
Then we can plug in different object uh
instances. Then we can create a
different variation of the environments.
Then each environment uh can be used uh
for training and evaluation. Uh so this
urban um we release to the public and we
also release a large scale 3D assets
which contains 100,000 assets with the
correct uh skills.
So for this kind of environment then we
can use the environment for evaluation.
Uh we also developed the pipelines to do
the post trainings with the simulation.
So basically we train the model first on
on videos through imitation learning.
Then we can put the models inside the
simulated environments and further do
post training to improve their uh
interactivity and the counterfactual
reasoning uh capabilities.
And so giving all those progress uh we
have this recent work we called the flow
pilot uh that can um implement this kind
of a real world sidewalk navigations um
from a single RGB cameras. So here this
robot only have one RGB camera then the
model will output uh the way points then
the controller will execute the next
point. Then you can see here um this
robot can handle this challenging
sidewalk navigations like know how to
avoid the collision with obstacles and
also how to interact with pedestrians um
properly.
Uh another very exciting uh direction is
this cross embodiment uh uh transfer or
deployment giving this sidewalk
navigation foundation model. We have a
research that to transfer this model
across different robot embodiment
without uh fight tooling. So this demo
video showing you that uh this model can
re work really well for this lagged
robots. We also have many ongoing
research that trying to transfer the
model to many other side robots uh like
the wheel lagged robots as well as this
electronic wheelchairs. Right? So in the
future, not only we can autonomously
deliver the food, we can also
autonomously deliver the people on the
sidewalk. Um so we release benchmark and
uh the code the the the codes uh at our
web page. So you can access the code and
papers from this barcode. So here I
would like to thank all my students and
the collaborators. Thank you.
All right, great. Thank you, Blet. I
think you someone left this.
All right, next up we have a workshop
from Lambda. Welcome up, Lambda. And
this is a one-hour session.
Come.
>> All right. Just the clicker for you.
>> You all set? You have any questions?
>> Thank you.
>> Start this time recording.
>> Sure. Thank you.
Cool. Uh, hi, my name is Davina. I work
as a researcher at Lambda. I work on
model evaluations and, uh, safety. Uh, I
basically come from a physical AI and,
um, self-driving background. So, uh, I
did evaluations and safety there as
well. I'm going to make a few analogies
to that, which is, um, which is why I
call that out. Um today I'm going to
talk about a month-long security
competition that we conducted with the
help of Berkeley RDI. Uh basically we
had teams compete as attackers and
defenders on a leaderboard uh and
compete against each other uh on prompt
injection challenges. Um we're going to
talk about you know how that went, what
we found out.
So why are we interested in prompt
injection? Um, let's talk about echolak
because that's the sort of production uh
incident that we want to be able to
catch before it happens. So, what
happened here was, you know, an attacker
sent an email to someone's inbox. Um,
this person didn't do anything. They
didn't interact with the email. They
just asked Copilot a question. Uh,
Copilot read this email. uh it read its
embedded instructions which were
harmful, complied with it and
exfiltrated their entire inbox. Um this
is the sort of thing that you know we
want to be able to catch with testing
and it is also really difficult to solve
because the root cause is architectural.
LLMs process uh instructions and data in
the same ch channel and they can't tell
when they are getting an instruction
that's wrong or ingesting data that's
incorrect.
So the talk is going to be in two
halves. The first half is going to focus
on the competition. Um you know 22 teams
took part uh both roles. There was one
month of live attack and defense. So
what changed, what improved uh how the
arena works, how we built something that
we think actually is measuring a real
signal and not just noise. The second
part is going to dive deeper into the
attack corpus. So what do these prompt
injection attacks look like? Is there
any common mechanisms that we're seeing?
So yeah, this is the competition. This
is what a u multi-prompt injection
competition look like. There is an
attacker agent. uh it's given a task and
a scenario and it inserts adversarial
text into that task. There's a defender
agent that's prevent uh presented with
all of that uh task and content and the
attack and uh outputs a structured
decision and there's a judge that
decides whether or not there was a
successful attack or not. So in this
competition there were as you can see we
had a public phase and a private phase.
In the public phase, we ran nearly
94,000 battles between different agents.
And in the private phase, we ran around
18K. So, a total of around 112. Uh,
we're going to focus on the private
leaderboard battles because I think
those would be more interesting. And to
note, this competition ran entirely on
GPTOSS 20B. So, any of the
vulnerabilities, any of the attacks that
we discovered are solely limited to this
one model. If we run this on other
models, we might find very different
results.
Um, here's an example of how a battle
goes. This is top of mind for me because
I'm working on Europe's rebuttals and
I'm sure a lot of you are too. So, the
defender here is an academic AC. They're
provided some context and a score for a
paper. The score is 5.3 and it's below
the threshold, so it should reject it.
But the attacker tries three different
approaches. starting with like some
vanilla persuasion
um which failed then using a system
notice injection which looked like it
could have worked but it didn't because
there was no basis for it. The attack
that finally worked is when the attacker
claimed that there's a data error in the
original upload and they uploaded a
corrected assessment which upgraded any
of the scores that were previously
present. So this is sort of the shape of
what a battle usually looks like where
the attacker sort of learns from what's
going on in the battle and gets the
defender manipulates the defender to do
something it should not be doing.
So um one thing that we think is super
important before actually talking about
the results of the uh leaderboard is how
do we know that you're actually building
a good realistic scenario? like how do
you know that you're not just measuring
noise? Uh for that reason, we created a
rubric uh to to measure what makes a
scenario meaningful. The first thing is
a scenario should be difficult. So if
you run one model against the same
model, they should have maybe like a 50%
balanced win rate. Uh this scenario
should be sensitive. So if you run a
strong model against a weak model, it
should actually be able to distinguish
between the capabilities. And third, you
want it to be, you know, you want this
uh scenario to not just be broken in one
round because that's sort of trivial.
Um, so using these three criteria, we uh
basically calculated scores to identify
bad scenarios and create better ones. An
example we show here is one of HR hack
where the target is like uh a salary
band uh and a single number. So you
don't need a jailbreaker to get this
output because you can basically binary
search the the answer. Like if the
target is 150, you can ask if it's
above, if it's below, and basically get
to the answer. So this is not a good
well-designed scenario. So we changed
this uh by making it an canary that only
the defender knows but not the attacker.
And so when it's leaked, it's clear that
there's an attack that has to succeed
and not just a binary search.
Um so yeah what did this month show us?
Uh so over a month 20 teams just like
battling it out on these boards. Uh the
interesting thing we saw is that
attackers initially improved but mainly
they flattened but defend defenses
improved a lot more. Um
the argument here is you know for
continuous red teaming what you really
want is you want to keep changing the
attackers and rerunning your red teaming
so that the defender who's living under
adversarial pressure can learn more. Um
second this is an example of like a
winning team and uh a winning attacker
team and a winning defender team and the
different strategies they tried
throughout the whole competition. So
you'll see that this timeline starts
around March 7th and ends around April
uh 1st. You'll see that they start with
the baseline attacker and defenders that
we provided. But then the red line uh
increases when they added a few more
strategies like attacker planning and
crit critique. Uh they also added defend
defending fingerprinting as well as
simulating the defender which by the end
gives them the highest score. Uh the
defender on the other hand mostly
focused on leak detectors uh payload
detectors and checking if the output
itself is validated before sharing with
the attacker.
Uh the second thing that mattered was
the public leaderboard actually cannot
see overfitting. So there were uh when
we ran the uh private leaderboard we
actually saw that the held out scenarios
were harder for everyone. The ASR median
dropped around 6.3 points. Uh 15 out of
22 of the teams actually stayed where
they were. Four of them fell really hard
and three of them did better. Of the
ones that fell really hard, we saw that
they had pretty like hard-coded
harnesses where they u conditioned the
response according to some hard-coded
texts and scenarios. And clearly we
caught that because we, you know, we ran
a private leaderboard. The lesson here
is don't trust your public eval set.
Always have a private hold out.
Um
let's see.
Now I'm going to talk about the
different types of attacks that we saw.
Uh basically we've saw these main 10
clusters and also I don't see the timer.
So someone tell me if I'm running out of
time. Okay. Uh so there were 10 uh
mechanisms that we saw in this attack
set. Uh the one that was super
interesting is cluster five which is
just ask nicely because the models don't
really understand the difference between
a harmful ask and just an ask. If you
just ask them for a password, they just
give this to you. This was actually an
attack that was develop like found in a
meta uh I think like a meta support chat
bot as well recently. Um, another one
that was interesting is uh C7, which is
the findings were wrong. So there's
clearly incriminating content in a
document, but then you append other
content that claims that the previous
findings were wrong and despite knowing
that they shouldn't trust the content,
the model still uh trusts it. Uh the
third one I think that was interesting
was fake pre-approval. So you claim that
a VP or someone of importance has
approved the action already that the
model is supposed to do and the model
complies with that. Um I yeah the more
interesting part to me was that four
mechanisms transferred across uh 14 of
the scenarios.
Um so just ask nicely fake pre-approval
findings were wrong workflow
impersonation they worked across the
board which basically says you shouldn't
build defenses around scenario specific
filters. Uh there are taxs that can just
work across various classes that you
should try to define your coverage with.
Um here's an example of what fake pre
fake preapproval look like. So in this
uh signature forge scenario, the
defender is an AP Clark which reads an
expense and uh approves a cost. There's
a 12K marketing event that clearly
exceeds the budget of 5K. Um but this
attack claims that the VP has already
approved it uh with some approval code
and that's seen as successful.
Similarly, uh inventory poison is when
um you know the defender is an industry
industrial supply agent and it reviews
contracts um and a normal minimum is 200
units but uh in this attack when it's
preapproved it it basically goes 50xit
normal and approves an order for 10,000
units. So the point is these are
different domains. um there was no
similarity between the actual scenarios
but the same attack worked.
Um the second thing is that you know
even in within one scenario various
different types of attacks can work. So
if you look at the cross-section of like
scenario and mechanism there are there
there can be different highlights.
different scenarios will have different
mechanisms that work against them and
different mechanisms kind of just
transfer across different scenarios. So
for this email fish attack uh workflow
impersonation as a mechanism works just
asking nicely works and findings were
wrong works. What's interesting about
this uh emailish scenario is that it's
actually inspired by echolak and it's
the same it's the same um workflow
impersonation is actually the same
mechanism that caused that failure.
So you know you can catch these big
events in this this toy data much ahead
of before they happen.
Um and yeah this fourth finding is a
little more interesting to me coming
from the self-driving space where you
know nearly 10% of wins have a near
identical failing twin where most of the
wording is the same but maybe two or
three words are different. So uh for
example in one of these scenarios you'll
see that owner confirmed via mobile app
just adding four words made an attack
from not successful to successful. Um,
this to me is cool because this reminds
me of the concept of near miss
collisions where basically in
self-driving if you uh if there's a
collision if if you go slightly
differently change your speed change
your angle uh very small conditions
about the attack or or or the scenario
then that's the difference between
something being a collision and not
being a collision.
So in summary uh what did this month of
open competitions show us? The first
thing is that defense is approved and
attacks sort of flatten. You kind of
expect this because a lot of the models
are fine-tuned for safeguards. Um the
important thing here is you should still
be using these models to red team
continuously and ideally use different
types of models because uh clearly under
adversarial pressure you you can find a
bunch of mechanisms that you wouldn't
find otherwise. This doesn't replace
human red teaming. It's more of like a
complement to human red teaming. Um the
second thing is yeah a held out set
caught all of the overfitting. So please
report a private number for your
benchmarks or always run your own
private eval and not just trust the
public data out there. Um
third thing is mechanisms transfer
across different scenarios but also uh
different mechanisms work on the same
scenario. And last of all, you know,
even if you test one prompt and it
fails, that might not mean that you're
secure because even slightly varying
that prompt in a different way, adding
three or four more, you know, words to
it can actually change how the model
perceives it. So test your near misses.
Don't just believe failure or success
outcomes at their face. So, uh, yeah,
that that's it. And I'm going to pass
this on to Tuan.
Um,
can you hear me? Good. Okay.
You have one more slides, Dina.
Dina. Okay. Anyway, so um by the way,
there's a NAM now we have a research
grant program. You can basically scan
this code. There's a link um where you
can submit an application form. U we
offer up to $5,000 cloud credit for
developers, researchers, um yeah um to
SP to support your work. We do have a
review process. Just give people a
little bit context here. And in the
first six months of this year, we
received about thousand applications. Uh
we granted like 350 applications. So
that's kind of scale we are supporting
right now. Yeah. Feel free to to to scan
the barcode.
All right. Cool. Um
now, okay, this is actually my slide. Um
yeah, I'm going to talk about what
happen if we pair cloud code with a
experiment tracker. I given the same
talk earlier this morning um more from
the research perspective. This one is
going to be more from the the software
itself and what's actually happened
behind the scene.
So just to recap, this is Gemma play the
Tetris game at the beginning doesn't
know how to play and scores nothing.
Then we had cloth watching Gemma play
and trying to help it to play better.
Over a period of two and a half days
were able to improve Gemma from scoring
zero to score 16.
And some basic rule here there's no um
the weights are fix are fixed for Gemma.
So no fine-tuning. Uh this is auto
research project. So no human
instruction is allowed. However, cloud
is allowed to change the model setting,
do promotization and inference speed up
and every single game has 30 minutes
timeout. So, Gemma has to think fast
enough. All right. Um, very quickly what
we learned is this is not only about how
smart cloud is. This is really about
like being very disciplined with doing
research project. Just imagine how human
will do research. Uh, we have a notebook
to write down our uh experiment notes.
We have a whiteboard and a sticky notes
for communication and broadcast result.
Uh we also have a signup sheet to coated
resource in the lab. Um the similar
version for AI agent are a bunch of APIs
that the agent can call to use tools and
uh this is our version of the API. Uh we
have open source software called the
lab. Um basically try to um approximate
everything human do and for agents. So
this is the back end.
Um I actually need to click things. I
don't know how I can click things.
[laughter]
Um text support is that way I can have a
like mouse or something. I can borrow
the laptop.
Uh no. Yeah. Here.
Cool. And I actually need to go through
this UI. I know how I can uh do this.
Is there a way I can
Um,
should I put it to an extended screen?
>> Extend the screen over.
>> Drag it over. Yeah, I'm trying to track
it over. There you go.
>> Okay,
then. Okay, here. All right. It's going
to be a little bit challenge, but uh I'm
trying to see from this monitor here.
All right.
Sorry. Uh continue to the side. Awesome.
So this is the front end of the lab. Um
so basically this is overview dashboard.
You can see um in the end uh Gemma is
able to score 16 points. It takes about
368 experiment to get there. It's been
experiments since the last improvement.
So the things gets more and more
challenging and the total cost is
$1.2,000 $2,000.
And like every single um auto research
project, you'll have this uh this graph
shows an improvement. And you can see um
what is kind of unique here is if you
hover your mouse to this record points,
you can see there's a cluster of result
and these are different experiment from
the same idea. So this shows the
performance of idea varies depends on
how you tune the idea. Um because of
that we also have a you guys
um cannot see
here. Yeah. Because of that we also have
a um
average score for each idea. Um
as you can see the average score is not
going to be as high as the maximum score
but the yellow points you can see
there's a uh overall um upward trend.
Now, um, let's go to
Give me a second.
It's
>> kind of weird.
school
idea.
U there should be a graph
um for idea tree which is not showing up
here. I don't know what's happening. Um
let me
no idea anyway. Um then I can go to
here. Let's dive into some of the ideas.
Anyway, so this is the first idea. Um
you have to believe me there's a g tree
where each each idea committed to its
own github branch. Um but I'm just going
to dive into a couple idea here. The
first idea is everything start from
scratch. What the lab's trying to do is
trying to um
establishes a baseline
where um basically trying some of the
offtheshelf Gemma models and the
different settings and see what open the
shelf gem model can do. The model you
tried are like 31B thinking of and on
and other smaller version of Gemma and
along this process the lab took some
notes about the finding for example the
first notes it took is it start to
realize there's a 30 minutes timeout
here so
it concluded so latency is a first class
driver of total score not just placement
quality so it's tend
prefer smaller models because it has
lower latency. However, uh a few
experiment later it almost flip its own
finding because you find out latency is
not the binding constraint here because
most of the game finished in 20 seconds
because of the top out. So it's really
not about the speed of your decision,
it's about the quality of decision
matters. Then you draw the conclusion
model inference knobs do not matter. The
problem is placement quality not speed.
Then start to move on to the second idea
which is trying to find a way to
survive.
Okay. I trying to see another idea here
uh which probably is more interesting. I
say idea five.
So this is idea five.
Um
and the idea five actually has a
milestone. I see what's happened here.
The milestone says breakthrough
discipline thinking producing the first
non-zero score. So this is the first
time the lab actually made geometric
score. So let's take a look what
actually happened behind the scene. We
can go back to the code divative here.
So this is all the change in this idea
branch. You basically change the prong
in certain way that uh it says reasoning
discipline critical. You have a token
budget. You think before answering but
your thinking must be short and follow
this six shorter line structure where
Gemma is supposed to first identify the
target location plus orientation then
test if there's a hole after the
placement then recommend the sequence of
move okay so this is the kind of a
instruction gem supposed to follow and
see whether Gemma actually follow the
instruction to do that we can see the
entire log
The nice thing about having certain
tracker is you always go back and check
what's actually happened behind the
scene. So this is the entire trace of um
that game jam I played.
Um let's see let's start from right from
the beginning.
Okay so this is the beginning. Um as you
can see now the game is so like
represented as a as ASKI code. So it has
20 rows 10 columns and you see how GMA
think about pro here thinking exactly is
trying to follow the same template.
First identify C0 to C2 which is uh
these three spot
um to place the pieces. Then think
whether it's going to be a hole. No the
board is empty. So any placement is a
flush. Then you recommend the sequence
of move to place the piece there which
is left left and hard drop.
Then in the next turn you can see the
piece is the first the previous piece is
put it here. The second piece is about
to drop. Then how did the Gemma think?
Again the target location is C3 to C6.
That's here. And uh check the hole.
There's no hole. Okay let's let's let's
do it. Then Gemma made a recommendation
of the sequence move. Then you realize
wait I'm already in the middle of the
board. So I don't have to move to right.
we just need to hard drop and
selfcorrect it. So having this log
allows us to inspect what's actually
happen behind the scene how Gemma
actually follow the instruction.
Um with the excitement tracker you can
also view the progress unit result in a
graphical fashion. you can actually
replay the game and with that we can
also um see some global statistics like
how long did the Gemma play the game and
how many turns how what is the latency
for each turn and how many token is it
cost. So all these sort of metadata
helps in the lab to like optimize the
strategy down the road.
Um, one more thing I want to show on the
UI is guess it's tools
sandbox. Yes. Um, as you know agent they
tend to cheat. So in order to prevent
them from cheating we can set up a
sandbox. In this case um it's really
about the fire access. We have to own
the experiment run inside of Docker. So
we have to specify which folders on the
host machine can be mounted in the
container and what are the files that
are read only. So cloud will not touch
those files. And this is the place where
you can set up a sandbox.
Okay, let's go back to the talk itself.
Um that's sort of like what's happened
behind the scene again. Um the
improvement from 0 to 16 does not come
in a smooth fashion. It comes in jumps.
I'm just going to walk through some of
the things actually made an improvement.
The first thing is as we said uh very
early stage cloud realize um it's better
to have a disciplined thinking template
and Gemma follow that. That is the first
milestone.
Um some of the other um things that
helps is for example um pick the lowest
hang where um if you see different
places just pick the bar that is lowest
and put your piece there. Totally makes
sense.
And u um don't be too greedy. Uh the
game is designed in a way that if you
clear two rows at the same time you got
three points which is very attracting
but um then after a few experiment the
lab realized Gemma was not able to
execute that strategy really well. It's
it's better just to pick the low noise
low foot and just take what you have
right now. Don't wait on it.
Um
at some point the lab created this
playbook which are the best practice for
individual pieces. So Gemma does not
need to think uh invent the move on the
fly
and um yeah don't overthink. This is
very important and it's very important
to put this u in the user prompt which
is a very last thing Gemma see before
you actually seen the board and start to
think and take actions.
It's also always nice to have fallbacks.
In this case, the lab also had the
strategy of put some piece to the left
as a fallback and put some piece to the
right of the for so it's balanced. You
don't put every piece to the same side
to p up the bar.
Uh there are also other things that the
lab tried that didn't work. Um here are
some of them. the the lab tried to use
the image screenshot instead of ask key
as the input because jamma is a
multimodel model however it didn't
really help because it eat into to much
token budget also too much thinking and
no no thinking um is not helpful you
need so like a right red right balance
right amount of thinking
on the infant side the lab did try the
speculative decoding and find out it
didn't work mostly because it is the
quality of the placement and matters
more than speed. However, it did use
quantized KV cache
on the prom side. Yeah, as I said, um
don't try to be too greedy. Play this
multiple row multiple lines in in a row
um um strategy basically just like pick
if you can clear a light clear a line
immediately. And also there are other
things for example try to disable
rotation at all because rotation is like
a hard thing to do uh to save time and
that didn't work.
Um yeah I guess in terms of how to use
this software um you can basically pip
install it from the GitHub then there
are three command you you you need to
run the first command is create a lab
workspace where your normal auto
research artifacts stored there and also
the database for the lab itself. Then
you have two command the first command
is launch the lab service all the APIs
and the front end. The second command
launch the lab agent. This is actually a
wrapper on top of your coding agent like
a cloud code or codeex. And the way to
launch this agent in a inside of wrapper
is allow you to directly talk to your um
um lab API.
So I have a little video record showing
how um how to install it and start the
first experiment. So this is how you can
pin install the software. Uh then uh we
have a tutorial repo you can basically
clone and reproduce the touches study
and after that I think at some point um
you launch the yeah the lab in it this
is the place to start the workspace and
there's one thing you need to do here
manually which is telling the lab your
research goal here we just give some
really high level ideas maximizing the
score that the gema model achieved.
ships while playing the Tetris game.
Then the lab is going to expand it into
a proper into a proper promd like all
your normal auto research project
and it takes a little while for the lab
to expand on this. I'm just going to be
I'm going to fast forward
and yeah, this is the expanded version
of the PR MD pron.m MD the lab created
as you see there's a structure the go
the background all that all right with
this as a PR MD
um what you can do is optionally create
a sandbox in this case uh we do need a
sandbox to make a bunch of files read
And after that I really cannot see it.
Um
yeah here I suppose I'm just going to be
very careful here to move forward.
Yeah, here you launch the lab service
the background back end the front end
and uh the last thing
you need to do is to launch the
progress bar is hidden so I cannot see
it. Um
yeah then you launch the the lab agent
uh eventually it basically as I said
it's a wrapper on top of cloud code
where when you launch in the cloud in
this way uh it directly talk to the lab
API and the code is get instruction API
to fetch all the research idea and the
project instructions and studies auto
research.
Um and uh after a while you can see the
first experiment is launching GPU is
free sandbox configured create the
baseline idea and launching run one and
it takes a little bit of time. I'm going
to fast forward to the end where you can
see here it conclude the first run the
baseline the baseline 1.1 score zero it
top out after 21 pace in 21 second and
uh create a 3.1 holes per placement and
some kind of final shape of the board
and the draw conclusion the finding is
that reframe uh the finding is the
objective isn't isn't really about
latency or scoring tactic it's about
survival
Yeah. So if you keep this uh the lab
running for a few a few hours, you will
start to score.
Okay.
Okay. Um just to close this part of the
talk, um I guess there's a lesson we can
that's a lesson we can learn from the
science history. Uh the the modern
science started not because like humans
suddenly becomes a lot smarter. Uh it
started because a bunch of people from
Royal Society including including this
gentleman called Robert Boyer they start
to exercise a habit that write
everything down very precisely so a
random people can reproduce it. And this
is also very important for auto research
agents because they are very powerful
minds can read a lot and make a smart
decision in seconds. However, um
everything will lost if they don't write
things down in the next session. Um yeah
and this is the QR code to get access to
this software. All right. Thanks.
Let's see.
All right. So, for the next part of the
talk, uh I'm going to be talking about
uh some of the work that I was doing. Uh
essentially, uh the model is not the
agent or what 300 million tokens of
agent traces taught us about models and
their harnesses. Uh my name is Zach
Mueller. I am the head of developer
relations over at Lambda. And
essentially back in March, uh, late
March, Clem, CEO of HuggingFace, made a
tweet essentially saying how we need
more open traces data sets because these
models are extremely smart, uh,
especially the large models that we
can't run at home. And the theory was if
you take the traces of these models and
train smaller models off of them, they
might be more performant. And
essentially, we took the task of let's
see what happens.
So the recipe looks fairly simplistic,
right? Identify a frontier, preferably
open source model so no one gets into
legal gray areas. Generate some
reasoning traces from it. So the
reasoning, the actions, and the results.
And then train a smaller model off of
those traces.
Well, then you get into this fun problem
of it's not actually about the model
because you can have Opus or you can
have Kimmy running in Claude codeex it
doesn't matter because the harness
itself dictates how well the model can
perform and a lot of times that answer
is not very straightforward.
For instance, uh this is on the terminal
2 benchmark. Uh and essentially what
folks were finding is take say Gemini 3
Pro which there's a Google Gemini CLI
harness for it. You would expect that on
a particular bench like coding you would
use the harness that the model was
trained for to be successful. And
instead, by changing to a minimal
well-crafted harness, not only could the
model outperform by 8%, it was also
cheaper by almost 20 bucks to run the
eval. And on the flip side of that, GPD
5.5 where we have Codeex and OpenAI
training these frontier models. Codeex
was better. It was 5% better. It was
also four times the cost because OpenAI
could have an incentive of well let the
model run harder, work longer to get
these problems solved and and add that
extra 1% boost. That's a valid
engineering concern. But what this means
is that you shouldn't always just stick
with one harness. You should experiment.
As another example, Kimmy K3 came out
last week and over 26 identical uh
identical tasks, a particular lab
decided to see which harness worked the
best by comparing performance, cost, as
well as time. To no surprise, the
harness that was built with the model
performed the best. Kimmy Code got 21
out of 26. It cost 54 cents and was
almost 300 seconds. Coming in second
place was Hermes Agent, which is an
open-source harness by News Research,
where it was almost performant, cheaper,
and faster by nearly 2 minutes. And then
there were a few other open- source uh
harnesses like Pi Agent and Open Code.
But one that I particularly found
interesting is Claude Code also scored
about a 19 while being three times more
expensive than the rest of them. This is
because cloud code injects a lot of
system prompts into their harnesses. And
so a lot of folks like to try out the
latest Frontier model in a harness that
might not work the best because most of
its context window is essentially being
battered by this system prompt. And so,
you know, it is a decision of maybe
every harness isn't best for every model
and we might not even know what harness
works best, but we have to at least try.
Now let's go into like what a trace is
in particular and just have a central
definition of it. So you the user will
in will prompt a model to say like
implement this function or implement
this server architecture or if you're
using codecs go get me frontier research
overnight. Good luck. Now what actually
happens inside the agent loop is it'll
reason for a while trying to judge what
its next step should be. It'll call some
tools and then come to a decision on
have we successfully fulfilled what that
prompt was. If not, this will go over
and over and over again until eventually
the model decides either we have a
solution or it needs human input.
Now, this matters because if we know how
the model behaves, then we could maybe
train a model later on on these traces
to have a better performant model with a
smaller uh total model size. So you
could run it at home, run it on like a
single H100, what have you. The problem
was we needed to come to a decision on
which harness to use. And we chose
Hermes agent. Um, at the time it was
only a few months old. We had a lot of
good uh partnerships with new research
and also I personally was using uh my
Hermes agent at home and not OpenClaw.
So I also had a personal bias for this
and so we went with Hermes agent.
Now that's step one, right? Now we
understand the world and how it's going
to interact with it. Step two is
deciding which models that Lambda should
go after for generating these traces.
And essentially it had to fall into
three buckets. First was it had to be
passively licensed because we didn't
want anyone to have to worry about can
these traces be used for business values
or for fun or even having them on your
computer. We wanted to make sure this
was freely available to the public and
to the community to do what they want.
Uh the second part is we also wanted to
make sure that we were targeting things
that the average person can't run at
home at the time. Uh because this was
back in March, state-of-the-art was Kim
K2.5 and GLM 5.1, one trillion
parameters, 800 billion parameters,
unless you happen to have four or 6,000
Blackwells sitting at home racking up
your electric bill. I assume most of us
can't really run this at home. uh and
then along with this I was paying
attention to the capabilities of the
models themselves. So at this point in
time GLM was state-of-the-art encoding
but this was the beginning of Kimmy and
introducing this Kimmy swarm paradigm
where in one reasoning chain you can
have multiple chains of tool calling
happening independently at the same time
which would be very valuable for these
small fast models to do at once.
And so this is you know sort of
recapping like if we have parallel tool
calling then as an example we could say
like hey let's go build this web service
real quick. Great. Then your open source
model can sit there and at the same time
start building the framework for like a
fast API route start the unit test for
them as well and then also keep track of
versioning changes and whatnot through
three separate different reasoning
traces at once. And you don't need three
different sub aents to do this.
Now, how we actually generated the
corpus was uh we had Kimk 2.5 come up
with about 7,000 different basic to
challenging coding scenarios. Uh it
covered anything from computer use to
you know build a basic hello uh world pi
file. Uh then we ran all of these
prompts through Hermes agent with
different models at the back end. So,
uh, that ended up being Kimmy and GLM
across 184 H100s about over a week. And
where we ended up was 150 million traces
from each model that were then verified
to make sure that the trace actually
made sense and was successful, then it
went into one bucket. If it was a
failure, that is still useful to learn
from. And it went to another bucket.
Uh and so essentially like within the
weekend after it got done, we just
released it uh and just saw what the
community would do. Uh and what happened
is it was actually very successful uh by
our book. So this is uh current. It has
about like 380 likes on Hugging Face and
about uh 3,000 monthly downloads. This
got up to about 10,000 during the first
month that we released it. But most of
all, we saw an interesting trend of
models that were trained based off of
the traces. Uh, Quus is a very common
model name and essentially it is a Quen
model trained on Opus traces. Uh, and so
you end up with this Quopus model. Uh
but essentially we were finding that in
the size ranges folks were training
these things from down to a billion
parameters to 27 billion parameters to
have a performant autonomous agent at
home that can be your assistant without
needing to have like thousands of
dollars of hardware to get that done.
And also we saw particular camps of
models being trained. So like first was
Quus right? So that's Quen 3.6 six. Uh,
and specifically, these were all non-m
mixture of expert models because in
general, folks were finding that when
you get down to this small of a model
size,
tend to matter less than having the
larger performant models, when speed
isn't per se a factor, when your agent
can run at home and you don't care if
the problem gets done in 12 hours or two
because it's just passively doing its
thing. Uh we saw a few interesting
experiments where folks would take like
the the Kimmy traces specifically and
try and bring this parallel tool calling
into extremely small models uh like
Liquid's LFM 1.2 billion. Sometimes it
was successful. I still think like 5 to
10 billion is the minimum to where you
can have these more complex uh sort of
tool calling capabilities. But it was a
very good effort. uh as well as some
other good Hermes specifically trained
models that were designed to work with
this harness. Uh Harmonic Hermes ended
up being one of the more popular ones uh
along with Quopus where their two models
combined had almost half a million
downloads and are still getting models
today.
And so essentially what I want you to
walk away from this talk is not per se,
you know, oh, you need to go distill
traces and go train your own model. I
challenge you to take the models that
you know and love and the quirks that
you love and hate about the harnesses
you use and take these models and shove
them into a different harness and see
how it reacts and behaves. It might have
an entirely different personality
because you don't have a 20,000
character system prompt guiding it. and
the model can be more expressive or you
might need to tone it down a bit because
codeex is so strong that it needs to be
wrangled and not just let loose. But if
anything, I hope that you can take away
this thought of, well, maybe if I use
codeex every single day, what happens if
I give it pi? What happens if I give it
Hermes agent? and just play with this
idea and start to widen your scope of
maybe one harness isn't always perfect
even if that harness comes from the
place where the model was trained. Thank
you very much
[applause]
and we'll be over here available for
questions if needed.
There you go.
All right, we have about I'd say 10 12
minutes until our next workshop. So,
want to take a little break and then be
back for 3:30. We're going to have
Replet coming up. Thanks.
All right, I think we're ready for our
next workshop.
We have Brandon from Replet that's gonna
talk about a bunch of things like live
coding. And welcome Brandon from Replet.
All right, mic check. One, two, one,
two. Thumbs up. Can everybody hear me?
Okay. Out there. All right, let's see.
Let's start the session with a little
bit of data. Um, let's see who's in
here. If you study data science, oh, you
want me to make this bigger? Yeah. Yeah,
let's do that. Okay, let's drag over
here.
full screen this.
How about that?
All right. So, this is what I want it to
be for right now. This is fine. All
right. Um, if you study or do stuff, if
you see yourself as a technologist, a
technology person, hands up. See who's
here. A lot of technologists. Um this
topic of vibe coding uh a lot of
non-technical people are getting into
building software these days. So if you
fashion and fancy yourself as
non-technical
uh and a vibe coded but you don't
necessarily identify as computer
scientist. Okay great great
so this talk will be a little bit about
uh both sides. I'll talk about some
technical topics. I'll take I'll talk
about some non-technical topics. Um, but
before we start, uh, I want to give away
a couple of pieces of merch. Um, I I see
you guys slumping a little bit. This is
the time of day where you need coffee
and you need energy. So, uh, first
trivia question about Replet. When was
Replet founded?
How old of a company are we? Just fancy
a guess.
>> More.
Seven more.
>> Who said 10? 10. All right. Winner.
Winner.
>> All right. Clap it up for this gentleman
here. Come get your prize.
I've got uh t-shirts and I've got hats.
I want I want to feel like a rockstar.
Should I Can I throw this hat to you?
>> All right. Second question. Um this is
an easy one. Who is the other speaker?
besides me. He's more famous on me than
I am. He was here earlier this morning.
Who spoke?
>> Sorry.
It might look like Michelle. It might
look like Michael, but his name is
Mckll.
All right. So, I'll give you a hat or
you want a t-shirt?
>> All right. T-shirt.
>> One more round of applause for this guy.
[applause]
>> All right. All right. And then I'll play
like rock paper scissors maybe at the
end of the talk uh for the other prizes.
But thank you guys. All right.
So coming over here
and full screen.
All right. It's still showing the that
window here.
Okay, let me drag this down.
Drag it.
This
>> I was trying to press it. Let me bring
drag it over. One second.
>> All right, let's see. Present.
No.
There. There we go. Present.
All right, we're going to go re reload
here. See if this works. Sorry, guys.
>> Okay. So, let's just drag this over
then.
And
for some reason this present is not
all right. Okay.
And I need my speaker notes now.
Can I have my speaker notes?
There we go.
All right,
perfect.
Can I have a round of applause for being
the tech guy that cannot even like
All right, so uh my name is Brandon
Middleton. I'm the head of education at
Replet. clearly not the head of AV uh
standing up here, but this talk is about
humans, human potentials big moment.
This was about 11 years ago. I stand in
the Guinness Book of World Records for
being the first person to rap hiphop rap
a commencement speech. I did the evening
and weekend NBA program. I graduated in
2015. If you want to hear the rap, come
meet me outside. Maybe I still remember
it after 11 or 12 years. Um this talk is
about how we can shift uh how we do
education and AI literacy uh in
classrooms in research in higher ed and
academia. And if you have thoughts and
questions and commentary about this
topic, we're in an experimentation
phase. There's a lots of uh trials to
try and things to succeed and fail at.
So I'll be uh offstage trying to meet as
many of you who are interested in this
topic. All right. Uh I deeply believe in
the power of education. Uh I've I've
taught outside of my regular job at
Amazon and at Microsoft and at other
places. Uh and at Replet, I actually got
the opportunity to full-time focus on
what I've been doing for the last seven
or eight years. So I get to focus on
universities and colleges and K through
12 and nonprofits that are focusing on
trying to bring AI literacy into like a
practical and tactical realm. So I'll
talk a lot about the work that we're
doing. I see some people that I've
worked with in the audience already. So
uh it's going to be a fun time here. All
right, let's blast off and go.
All right, so I'm going to try to make
this talk like also a demonstration of
how you build an end toend application
using a platform like Replet that uh has
agentic AI embedded inside of it. Um
hands up if you've ever used agents or
agentic AI to build anything. Okay,
almost the whole room. Hands go up. If
you build something today, hands up.
All right. So, if you go to this actual
URL here, I'm afraid to do this because
I'm afraid that uh we'll pop out again,
but there's an app that I created this
morning. Uh this.
All right. So, if you click that URL,
it'll take you to a page that looks like
this. And if you click that wall, this
button here, [snorts] there is a picture
of
all of our new joiners here. I used
Replet agent to actually
let's see
to actually uh build this application
out. Man, this is killing me.
So if you would like to leave a message
or if you would like to uh literally
participate in this scroll wheel scroll
wall, this is an example of something
that's using agentic AI and agents in
order to build. It accepts your images
or your messages and then it will put
this scroll wall together in the back
that you'll be able to see. All right.
All right. All right. So, I'm going to
go there and looks like you can see all
of you guys' images popping up on the
screen there. Uh, great job and great to
meet everybody virtually. Um, is this
the first demonstrate like live demo
demonstration that you guys have seen
today? No. Okay, you've seen a little
bit more. Well, keep doing this if you
like. Uh, put images, put comments and
commentary, but this is one example of
uh of agentic AI like at work. All
right. So, let's go back to presentation
here and
keep going.
All right. So, I've taught uh at the
Stanford Design School, I teach a class
every spring quarter called Redesigning
Finance. And I've had students like joke
to me about kind of the state of higher
education. And we c us calling it that
as educators because of the price of the
tuition and not necessarily um how fun
it is to be in class or uh the quality
of the content or the differentiation
between being in class or going to
YouTube or going somewhere else to learn
the same kind of kind of information.
And so there's a lot of uh truth in
justest sometimes you know you get
students to ri you and give you a sense
of like man the return on investment as
I believe in the American dream to get
me a job and to do everything that
people have told me to do that's
starting to wayne a little bit. Um if
you've heard some of that sentiment from
students or if you feel a little bit
like that yourself uh give me a hand
wave. There's a few people who are like,
"Man, it's tougher to get a job or it's
tougher to believe in the status quo
these days." So, I feel like the reason
that some of these jokes work is because
there's some truth to this, right? We
need to actually think about how exactly
it is we're going to reimagine uh
education as a whole. What is it for?
How do we do it? and how do we build the
bridge from higher ed, higher
institution of academia into kind of the
workforce. Uh workforce development is a
little bit of what I focus on uh at the
K through 12 level all the way through
college and then into early early career
at Replet. All right. So, what we did to
try to talk to people in a groundup
fashion is go on what we're calling a AI
literacy tour. So, I've been to Chicago
this summer where I'm from, born and
raised. I got a 708 number in Michael
Jordan shoes. That's all I got left from
Chicago. I've been in the Bay Area for
like 21 years now. Um, we've been to
Chicago, we've been to New York, we've
been to Los Angeles, we've been to
Atlanta, we're here in the Bay Area
talking to people about what it feels
like to be a student at this time. what
it feels like to be a teacher, receiving
mandates from the top and trying to like
translate AI literacy into something
meaningful for yourself and then for
your students and community. And
what we're trying to move towards is an
answer to try to reimagine what
education actually looks and feels like
because in certain places uh I I think
that it's it it is for sure failing. All
right.
What's happening?
Wi-Fi
here.
All right. So, the education system as
it currently exists was actually
designed pretty well. Um, it was
designed hundreds of years ago um for a
world that today is not really existent.
uh information itself used to be um
scarce. So you needed to come to a
university in order to actually uh
receive it from a professor who was the
kind of the end all and be all. Uh you
come to receive and retrieve that
information from your professor. Uh the
knowledge was locked up in libraries, in
laboratories, in lecture halls and the
world like remembered the answer and
used the answer um that you were
receiving. It was often the evidence of
your learning if you knew the actual
answer which is not true today. Like you
can have uh a lot of book knowledge and
no street smarts. You can have a lot of
things that you've observed but maybe
that is all information misinformation
or disinformation. So today uh
information is not scarce literally
everywhere. Answers are abundant and
increasingly the intelligence itself is
becoming uh pervasive and abundant as
well. So how do we move into an
intelligence age where the cost of the
the models are dropping but the
intelligence of the models is actually
getting really really good. Um how do we
replicate and how do we as an industry
within uh education think about how to
wield uh this intelligence moving
forward for technology and non-technical
people who are going to be using these
platforms.
So this massive like civilization level
shift uh creates a big like
uncomfortable question for the
institution of higher ed. Uh if we were
designing college for today like summer
of 2026 and we could start with a blank
canvas and a blank sheet of paper um how
exactly would we go about doing that?
Will we still organize everything around
lectures in um in libraries and will we
create semesters that are 16 weeks long
still or would we make things shorter?
Um will we count attendance? Does that
matter in the future of education? Um
close book recall and wrote memorization
of things on final exams. Is that a
thing that we need to hold on to or
something that we should throw throw
away?
We've confused uh time served in college
institutions with with learning, right?
We've confused the credentials with a
student's capability to actually
perform. And sometimes we've confused uh
sorting students throughout four or five
years with actually educating them. So,
college has become this extraordinarily
expensive sorting system. And we sort by
admissions. Sometimes we sort by grades
and departments. uh sometimes we're
sorting by the actual institution that
that person or those people went to. Uh
and then the the result of it at the end
of four or five years uh we call merit
and we literally like will hire or not
hire on the basis of that sometimes. So
I think a lot about that at Replet and
uh what we've been doing on this AI
literacy tour or campaign across these
five different cities is literally
asking people from preschool teachers
lady in the back is a preschool teacher
uh all the way up through research uh
researchers and professors at uh R1 tier
one universities like what what's
happening how can we incrementally
choose small experiments and things to
peel off and try that might be useful in
defining what education is going to look
like in the future. So in this session
like this is me uh in the community in
East Palo Alto. I live in Palo Alto and
and do a lot of community work in East
Palo Alto. And we had a session of seven
year olds in the room all the way up to
elders 77 year olds in the room. and we
were talking about the issues of uh
resource allocation and different things
that plague the city of East Palo Alto.
And I'm using these sticky notes to put
things uh on paper. I'm using my phone
and applications to actually capture the
things that the seven and 8 year olds
are telling me as well as the things
that the 75 and 76 year olds are telling
me. And I'm using Replet as a platform
to basically like you're doing with your
photos um upload that to an application
and think with AI as a partner uh and
show the community exactly how easy it
is to do even though they themselves
didn't identify uh as computer
scientists and engineers.
All right. So meanwhile, the work world
outside of the community aspect is
sending us some pretty staunch messages.
And uh couple of stats for you. At the
beginning of this year, 2026, uh
unemployment amongst young recent
college graduates was about 5.7% so just
under 6%. Um, more strikingly about 41
and a half% were undermployed, meaning
that I might have graduated from a
really fancy school, but I might be
working in something that's really
underneath my intellectual capability or
even my interest, which is also a
problem. So, we have that to deal with.
Uh, this doesn't mean that the college
institution uh in it in and of itself
doesn't have any value. It means that
the connection between education uh
student capability and opportunity is
currently under strain and we need to
solve for that. The World Economic Forum
reports that nearly 40% of workers
current skills are expected to change
between this year and 2030. So that if
you had a hundred people um representing
every of the eight billion people on
earth uh 59 out of those hundred people
would literally have to shift and
reskill and repivot within the next four
years. So that's how much change uh we
have to um think about and that's why I
hold everything with a really loose grip
because everything in AI changes so
quickly. All right. So if the global
workforce is going to change and a
diploma can't be the finish line, you
know, what do we do? uh maybe that
diploma is not even like the reliable
map that we should be using in the
future as we rebuild this thing. So the
real advantage as I've seen it has uh
come from the ability to actually learn,
the ability to unlearn and the ability
to pick things back and back up and
relearn them uh as I move forward. Uh I
graduated from UIU as an electrical
engineer. I came out to the bay to work
at Cisco systems as a networking
software engineer and I went to hos
business school in graduated in 2015. I
started to put down a lot of my uh
technical skills in terms of programming
in terms of product management that I
used to do. But these days you know I
left AWS after six years to join Replet
as the head of education. I'm actually
picking back up some of those skills of
product management, some of those skills
within the EPD triangle of design and
engineering and product management in
order to build experiences for people
that are both technical and
non-technical as we move forward. So,
uh, relearning, unlearning, and learning
to learn is uh really a core skill if
you're going to be a contributor to this
education of the 21st and 22nd century.
All right. So AI is not the next edtech
gadget. Um I see AI a little bit
differently than I see the calculator
for example. Uh a little bit different
than like a Google search engine from
2003 and 2004. Uh I see it as not only a
way to automate things like grading or
summarization of papers that you might
receive as a professor or a way to
generate lesson plans. But AI gives us I
think a once in a century opportunity to
actually rebuild education around human
potential. So I think each of us have an
innate like passion, desire, skill to be
able to do and deliver something to the
rest of the eight plus billion of us on
this planet. And I think we can use vibe
coding and use agentic AI in order to
help humans achieve like peak
performance in their fullest potential
moving forward.
For the first time in history, I think
imagining
agentic assistants and personal tutors
uh is a real thing that can be achieved
and grasped within the next couple of
years.
All right. So, this is a picture of me
like in the community. Again, this is,
if you're not familiar, a guy who was
signed to a record label uh for 10
years. Five years ago, he got um
released from that initial deal where he
did three albums, Grammy, won a Grammy
and all of that. He came to the Replet
office asking not so much about Agentic
AI and technical terms, but he launched
out as an entrepreneur and said, "Hey, I
want to run a record label and do a lot
of things that plagued me when I was
part of the larger music industry.
things like revenue recognition for the
amount of royalties I should receive
when I stream my music across all of the
different uh platforms like Spotify or
YouTube Music. Uh you get fractions and
fractions of pennies for doing that. And
he would actually go about trying to
audit the money that he would receive.
And the runaround that he described uh
in the errors and all of the things that
were basically swept under the rug that
most other artists weren't doing, he
thinks is a big opportunity. So, he's
building a new record label and using
vibe coding even though he hasn't really
got that computer science and that
technical background in order to
reimagine things in the music industry.
Um, even though he's not uh part of an
actual university right now, this also
falls underneath the umbrella of uh
education uh in my in my scope at
Replet. Music education, there's
business education, there's technology
education. So, um, if you if you've got
thoughts around things that s typically
will sit outside of the the university,
uh, I'm happy to talk with you guys
onetoone about that as well as I as I
leave the stage.
All right,
so let's talk about this personal tutor
for every learner. uh not only for like
wealthy individuals like a lot of uh
folks that are neighbors of mine in
PaloAlto will send their kids to
Saturday school or they get out of
school at 3:00 and they're not home
until 6:00 because they've got these
personalized tutors for STEM subjects
and for other things. But I think that
students whose parents know how to
navigate the system, that's pretty soft.
But for the ones that are not confident
to raise that hand in a crowded lecture
hall, um it's cool to think about how we
can use Agentic AI to build personal
tutors that will be available 24 hours a
day 2 a.m. when that student who's too
shy to raise their hand in lecture hall
needs a question answered. Uh students
who need an explanation in an
alternative way. Maybe you're visual and
not auditory learner. Maybe you need uh
or maybe you perform well in oral exams
versus taking written timed exams. Uh
there's lots of examples of students
that need accommodations and have them
in order to learn at their best. And the
ability to personalize education uh
without any embarrassment uh exhaustion
or judgment on behalf of the student and
the teacher who sometimes is in a one to
many type of forum is something that we
think a lot about at Replet.
uh multilingual support, lingual support
is something that in the Bay Area like I
I lived in Chicago so I heard a little
bit of Spanish but mostly English when I
came uh came out of Cal or came out of
Illinois and towards California when I
arrived here like the concept of pretty
much everybody speaking at least like
two languages. I felt like a total
slacker um for the first several years
uh of my life. If you speak more than
one language um give give me a hands up.
So I am underachchieving all of you
essentially by only speaking English.
But um I think agentic AI can really
help with that too. Like you can speak
into Replet as a platform uh English
just as well as you can do French or
Spanish or any uh other of your native
tongues and then have that translated in
apps that you build to other people who
speak uh different languages on the
other side of that interaction. All
right. Uh so I don't see what we're
talking about as replacing teachers. I
think the teachers themselves have
really important work to do. Uh so that
we're talking about expanding the reach
of what one individual is able to do for
a classroom of sometimes 15, sometimes
50, sometimes a hundred people at a
time. So when the teacher becomes less
of a broadcaster uh and more of a
designer and a coach and a mentor, a
critic and a community builder, I think
the students um have a lot of room to
thrive and a lot of room to grow into
leadership and ownership um as they move
towards uh towards what's next for them.
An AI can definitely deliver the
information, but what the teacher needs
to do and why that matters is a very
personal kind of that care, that
concern, that thing that is uh
intangible a lot of the times, that
belief that the teacher has in that
student that will uh allow them to stay
up that extra couple of hours and
complete something or have pride in the
work that they turn in as a result of uh
the seeds that were planted in in them
by that teacher. All right.
So, this is my future. I've got three
startups, one age 14, one age 10, and
one age seven. Um, basically at the end
of every pay cycle, I like empty out my
wallet to do things that make them
happy. And I think a lot about when I
get out of bed, I'm excited to
contribute to this future because I know
that uh four years from now, uh the
oldest startup is going to go into
college. And in 2030, who knows like
what learning, what education, what like
credentiing, what college, what work
even will be. Uh if you have ideas about
this and you feel like you know what's
going to happen in 2030, uh ple please
see me immediately after this
presentation. Um so this is
this is special to me in that I think
the experimentation window that we have
is about a year year and a half maybe
two years to try all of these things and
see what sticks and see what does not
stick. Uh we have a program that we run
at replet called our faculty fellows
program. I see uh one person in the
audience that's a part of us. Dr. Chin
wave at wave at everybody. Um we do a
monthly webinar where people who have
said yes to experimentation
um use a replet platform to build out
experiences and to build out things and
they put them in front of students or
they use them in their research and then
report back to a cohort that's now about
75 teachers large and we talk through uh
what worked uh what didn't work and we
try to share that information in
community so that uh the next person who
has yet to dip their toe in the water
feels a a little bit more comfortable
and confident doing that on the back of
that shared experience. So, I'm hoping
that my kids uh see enough at home and
are able to learn enough from these
communities at our building to be
confident to experiment themselves as
they go uh into high school and into
college.
All right,
so let's um let me show you the Replet
interface. If you've seen Replet itself
before, raise your hand.
Okay. Um, can I get one volunteer to
explain uh what Replet is to somebody
that's never never used it before? One
volunteer from the crowd. I'm Go ahead.
In the black shirt,
explain what Replet is for someone who's
never used it.
Oh, who has never used it? Okay, so you
are not the person [laughter] to answer.
Um, right here in the blue shirt. Yes.
>> Love that. So he said from idea to built
AI application without the requirement
of knowing much about the technology
underneath. So, uh, I'm gonna since I
already gave you a hat, I'm going to
give you this to give to somebody else.
Thank you, sir.
>> Yeah, you guys can mob him after. Um,
but the actual like replet interface, if
I come out of here
and
let's see.
Okay, here. All right. So, this is like
the replet interface. I'm going to come
over
here.
All right. So, you get a prompt box like
this, which is a very, you know, natural
I've done this with chat gpt. I've done
this with claude before. And
essentially, if you click import here on
the actual screen, you if you want to
start from something that you've already
been building in another place, you can
import uh work from other places into
Replet. If you want to like uh check the
status of other projects that you've
been working on as you continue to build
out things in Replet, you'll get a full
page of all of the different things that
you've done. I built this slide
presentation in Replet. As you guys
know, um talk about like integrations
with other pieces of technology that you
probably interact with on a day-to-day
basis. All of the different connectors
that we have are personal and enterprise
types of connectors. So, I personally
use a lot of like Dropbox and Discord
and um you know, Slack and Google Drive.
Uh, if I scroll all the way down, there
are 511
different integrations that you can be
prompting and you can say, "Hey, Replet,
um, go grab my Google Drive, my Dropbox,
and my data bricks and my Google Sheets,
for example, and I want to make an
application that uh, does XYZ." So, it's
a lot more fun to connect into all of
these applications before you build the
thing that you want to build out. All
right. Um, let's go to
back here
back home.
So, the artifact and the output types
you see website here, mobile app,
design, games, uh, you know, we built
that photo app in a few minutes here. So
these are all the different kinds of
artifacts and expressions that you can
put into this prompt box and kind of
steer the model towards. So if you know
you want to build a slide deck, just
click the slide deck button. If you know
you want to build a mobile app, iOS,
Android, click the mobile app button and
that'll steer Replet in the direction
that's necessary in order for you to
start uh that back and forth
interaction.
Uh on the bottom left here, there's a
learn and a documentation uh button
where we've spent a good amount of time
uh putting video content together to
take people from zero to 100 and then
from 100 a little bit further. Uh if you
are not familiar with vibe coding,
you're not familiar with like building
with AI, um the documentation in some of
these learn apps are uh really helpful
for that. Okay.
And
Coming back here,
this once you've actually kicked off an
actual work session, you can see that
there's a number of modes. So, there's a
light mode here, which allows you to uh
ask very basic questions like, "Hey, can
you change the color, like the
background color of my slides from black
to orange? Can you change the text of
this slide to say this instead of that?"
Um, that's what light mode is for. Um,
economy mode is like the default middle
of the road like reasoning,
intelligence. Um, and then when you want
to do things that are really, really
ambitious, you can go to power mode. And
for each of these, you've got the
ability to kind of click into
these and select either close models or
open models depending on the level of
work that you're trying to do. So, uh,
model choice and the ability to actually
choose the right model for the right
thing that you're asking Replet to do
is, uh, is part of the experience here.
All right,
so that's a little bit about the Replet
platform itself.
Let's check on our application here and
see if we've got any new faces.
All right, Dr. Chen, you're looking good
there.
Love to see love to see you guys doing
that. All right,
let's talk about let's keep going with
the actual presentation itself.
Come full screen mode here
present.
Okay.
All right.
So let's talk about responsible AI use
and like how we can do assessment a
little bit differently. So we have to
change the kinds of things that we
value. Uh I think testing is pretty dead
at this point. In my class redesigning
finance I usually am asking students to
YouTube record explanations
uh five to seven minutes at a time of
them grappling with a topic uh in
finance that we're discussing. So, one
of the themes from last year's class was
how do you deal with um catastrophes
like the LA wildfires that happened a
couple years ago. If you are trying to
redesign reinsurance and the insurance
industry and improve the claimants's
experience for the next fire that
happens in LA or the next flood that
happens in Florida, how do you actually
go about designing something at the
claimant level, at the insurer level, at
the reinsurer level, and have students
literally build stuff and then actually
defend what they've built um
synchronously. So unless they've learned
how to master deep faking, uh they're
putting like the work into actually
thinking through it and putting a
prototype and uh their video next to it
as a submission. So I think we should
stop designing assessments around stuff
that machines can do well and start
designing uh with the human being in
mind and each human being actually has
different capabilities. So I in my own
grading have done some adaptive type of
work. It's all group work, but we look
at the students uh grade in school. So,
freshman through master students. We
look at the students background in uh
engineering versus I'm a a brand new
coder or a brand new person to
technology. Um and we grade across
things like the fidelity of the design
that they put forward. uh the
collaboration that they've showed within
the group as measured by how their
teammates are voting and not necessarily
how uh we the uh we the teachers and we
the TAs look at them. So these are a
couple of ideas about how to change
assessment in terms of moving away from
uh exams or pop quizzes and more towards
experiential and building. All right. uh
taking away judgment, curiosity, um
care, originality, and collaboration.
Like, if we remove these things and
they're already absent from the system,
I don't think we're setting ourselves up
for success. So, let's lean into uh
empathy. Let's lean into uh the ability
to frame problems, worthwhile questions
to ask, get uh high points, even if you
don't have the answers to them
necessarily in the classes that I've
been teaching over the last year or two.
All right.
All right. The question should no longer
be, did the student use AI? But better
questions that we should be asking
ourselves as educators are, did the
student actually think? Did the student
verify the work that they put forward?
Did they site sources, say where it came
from? Uh, did the student improve the
work? Did the student explain the
decisions and the choices that they made
in order to get to the output that they
actually came to? Can the student defend
the conclusion? And can the student tell
us where the machine and the machinery
actually got it wrong? They're using
their own judgment. They're using their
own expertise in a particular area to uh
make judgments about what the machine
said. So imagine this oral defense after
every major individual or group project.
Uh imagine students submitting um not
only one final answer but a tracked like
record of their reasoning. I built a
system inside of Replet that allows
students to actually reflect on
lectures, submit the actual assignments,
and then for them to be able to track.
Again, um the space between two
lectures, you might have learned a lot.
The space between one exam and the next
exam, you might have learned a lot. And
the traditional system that we live in
doesn't necessarily capture those
moments. So, we've got the ability to
build new software and new artifacts
that will help us to actually capture
some of that. All right. Um, let's keep
moving here. Uh, this is a picture of a
hackathon. Um, this is an interesting
story because I didn't do particularly
well in like molecular and cellular
biology and chemistry or any of the
things that this hackathon in San
Francisco was about. But the students
use the replet platform in order to uh
find biomarkers in order to uh do things
around drug discovery to do some life
sciences innovation and my commentary to
them as a judge you know one of the many
judges was about um how deeply they
thought about the solution how many
people they surveyed like their process
uh a little bit more than like my domain
expertise and I think all of us even if
we don't go deep into a particular ular
area um or domain can offer kind of our
lived experience and our perspective to
make the stuff that students are
building a little bit better.
All right, this uh this is the hand of a
of a high school student in Chicago uh
15 years old named Jack. Um he comes to
school from like 2530 miles outside of
where the school is actually at. And uh
the principal of Holy Trinity High
School gave students access to Replet in
this this last spring. And Jack decided
to take the school's uh disciplines and
the things that they hold high in terms
of the school principles and he built
out this system that he gave to teachers
and teachers are able to identify things
that align with the school's values and
principles and literally the teachers
can use their mobile phones to basically
reward and say yes that's exactly the
exemplar behavior or the um care and the
collaboration that we want to encourage.
So they're literally like changing the
environment and the culture of the
school. And they use the digital signage
as students are walking in from the
buses like into the lobby every morning
in order to show like a a leaderboard of
sorts of the students that are getting
uh he put XP. So the students are
getting XP in this application on the
digital signage and they're getting like
uh the positive reinforcement uh that
they all seek. and you can use your XP
that you accumulate in order to do
special things in this high school. So,
this whole gamification and this idea of
the culture of the school being improved
and enhanced on the back of a vibe
coding platform was something that was a
really cool thing uh that I heard in our
Chicago stop of the uh AI literacy tour.
All right. And then when I asked Jack
about like how he thought about learning
uh AI, this is how he broke it down for
me. He said learning with AI. So using
it as a tutor, collaborator, critic,
translator. He talked to me about
learning about AI. So they have um one
teacher in the entire school that did a
deep dive like a professional
development um about a year ago and then
brought what he learned to the
sophomores, juniors, and seniors in the
class. And essentially all of the stuff
that the students picked up from that
teacher uh was basically about the
security, the governance, the how models
and algorithms actually work and from
that he got inspired to learn beyond AI.
So he solved things around uh connecting
his application and streaming it via
Bluetooth to the digital signage system.
um he learned a little bit about the
community impact and the issues in the
community around Holy Trinity High
School. So he talked to me about things
that were beyond the technology in his
presentation of his solution to me when
I visited the school which was
interesting. So I think three modes to
start with in terms of uh learning with
AI, learning about AI and then learning
beyond AI.
And we think about how this can like
move way beyond the classroom outside of
technology and into stuff like medicine,
into stuff like justice, uh, resourcing,
and then education like we've been
talking about. Um, I think we're going
to quickly get into a philosophical and
ideological conversation when it comes
to uh, AI and education because there
are certain things that technology
cannot necessarily cure that we've had
in society for a long time. We've had a
lot of uh, economic inequality. We've
had a lot of uh poverty and war and you
know different things that sometimes
money is a factor in but it's not able
to be cured and solved all the way using
technology. So I'm excited to be able to
talk more to communities and to students
about these ideological and phil
philosophical principles in addition to
the AI uh literacy and foundation that
we're giving them.
All right, so let's take a quick break.
Um, anybody know who this guy is?
This is uh the the biggest little kid
I've ever met. So, in December, um, me
and Amja, the founder of of Rep, got to
teach Shaquille O'Neal how to vibe code.
And this is so weird. His hands are so
huge that I wanted him to type prompts.
He literally his hands are too big. He
can literally not type. So, I asked him
to open up multiple tabs in the browser.
I said, "Hit F5 and then just start
talking." So, in the span of 90 minutes,
we were on set in Atlanta and we got to
uh we we made something called Shack
GPT. So, he wanted to answer every
sports question. We we hardcoded Charles
Barkley sucks into any question
regarding Charles Barkley, his his TNT
like broadcaster mate. Uh we made
another one called uh Shack Daddy. He
said, "Uh, Brandon, I want to solve the
loneliness epidemic in America. There's
a lot of single men that need to know
how to talk to women, and we need to get
these men married." And so, we we made
Shack Daddy a pickup line generator for
all of the men in America to uh I see I
getting some laughter back there. Okay.
Uh he made another one to track all of
his advertisements. You've seen Shaq on
like radio and TV and movies. Like I
think Snoop Dogg might be him and Snoop
Dogg are like neck andneck by putting
their brands like everywhere. So we made
a a way to track all of his investments
to see like year-to date 2026 until now
or all time like how can I understand my
return on my time and my brand and it
was a lot of fun to see him be ready to
use his brand and to see him be
vulnerable and be okay like not knowing
things. And this is part of my vision
for the uh AI team, the education team
at Replet to take people who have uh the
willingness and the humility to actually
try new things and then once they've
accomplished it, kind of take it to
their audiences, take it back to their
alma mater, like Shaq went to I think
Louisiana State, like LSU. So, if you um
have ideas about how to scale this on uh
a platform or on a person that other
people are looking up to or other kids
see as cool, uh this is actually part of
uh my strategy uh in the education team.
And as we get into back to school
season, you'll see our team do a little
bit of this with hopefully Shaq and many
many other folks that uh can can
incentivize kids to learn learn these
these principles. All right. Um, I think
we got about 15 minutes to go. What I'm
going to do is pivot. I've got a couple
of these slides that you can um see as
we move towards the back end of this.
But essentially what I want to leave you
guys with is five commitments and these
will be things that teachers,
researchers, I'm hoping that students
can um grock these and use these as we
move forward. Uh the first is to
guarantee AI access for every student.
So I'm encouraging schools from the
universities that are well resourced all
the way down to like I think middle
schools and high schools is a probably
appropriate place to put this. Um
redesigning assessment like we've talked
about about around critical thinking as
opposed to this is the right answer and
this is the wrong answer. I think a
spectrum uh is worth considering. Uh
there's a lot of gray area in the life
that we live today. uh rewarding
teaching innovation as seriously as we
do research. So pretty stark contrast uh
within academia I think um in terms of
rewarding good teaching versus rewarding
uh research. So, it'd be cool to see
higher ed um take more to uh shining a
light on great teachers and people who
are able to facilitate and to coach and
to teach cohorts of folks 25, 50, 100 at
a time into this AI literacy. That's a
big opportunity for us. Uh replacing the
one-time degree with lifelong learning.
Uh a couple years ago at Stanford, we
actually as like adjuncts talked about
kind of this on-ramp off-ramp idea. So
that once you started in the
institution, you literally like are
Stanford for life. And then whether you
come off at 25 and come back at 30 or
you come off at 45 and come back at 47,
the idea that we'll have enough as human
beings to like learn and that the
university context can be a community.
Um that's kind of a lifelong thing is
something that I think uh worth
discussing. uh the economics of it and
like the uh the exact way to implement
it is still an open question but uh this
community that humans need is something
that is um is already understood and
then lastly uh measuring capability and
mobility uh and not rankings as much. So
I think um credentiing and the ability
to have students have a proof of work
system as they look to graduate and find
jobs for the future is a big opportunity
for us. Um, I mean I thought in Jess
like it'd be fun to have a funeral
service for the resume, for the
transcript, maybe for the GPA because in
the future I think where we're going to
land is a place where you're going to
point me to your portfolio of built work
and all of the proof of things that
you've done in projects collaboratively
and solo over time. And then as I'm
sitting across the table in an interview
from you, your ability to communicate,
to tell the story, to show me the actual
um forks of options that you had and the
ones that you chose and why will be the
determining factor about whether I'm
excited, you know, personally to bring
you onto my team or not. So, uh you
know, measurement, capability, and
mobility over rankings, I think, uh is
an important concept to think through.
All right. Um, in the last few minutes,
what I wanted to do is give you guys a
crash course in
the design of an actual application. So,
let me come down from this. And if you
wanted to check this presentation out, I
will uh if you go to that app that you
just opened up and do like uh AI
foundations deck uh AI foundations deck
after you do 2084-edu.replet.app,
you can get to this entire deck and I'll
send it out. But uh with the with the
remaining few minutes, I wanted to talk
a little bit about uh a vibe coding just
101 type of session. So, let me play
this from the start. And for all of you
who had not necessarily built anything,
uh, this is going to be like a 10-minute
just lightning fast way to think about
building your first app or building your
end toend app using using Replet. All
right, you guys know who I am. We talked
about what Replet is. One thing I did
not talk about is how you can invite
multiple developers into your project so
that maybe solo uh myself and Dr. chin
start to make something, but then we
want to invite two or three other people
into it. There's an invite button on the
top of the workspace that allows other
developers to be prompting the same uh
body of code as you. So that in the same
way that you can build out a Google doc
with four, five, six people, you can do
that building uh software in Replet. So
that's a pretty powerful concept to
think through. All right. In terms of
your first prompt, um I typically will
start somebody who's never prompted
anything with just like a personal
portfolio page. So you can say, "Hey,
make me something um that'll help me to
express what I've accomplished in my
career." Uh you can throw in a picture
of yourself and say, "Repick, go make
it." Um, after that's done, we've got
the concept of abstracting all of the
underlying infrastructure, the hosting,
some of the database information, some
of the uh security scanning, and all of
that stuff that you need to do to go
from local host on your laptop to fully
deployable so that when somebody clicks
the actual URL, it works for everyone.
Uh, that's what the publish uh inside of
Replet does.
after we've got like a design that's up
clickable, you know, front page with
maybe our face on it, the idea that we
want people to actually interact with
our app requires the adding of a
database. So, when you guys uploaded
your pictures into the app, um if it was
just a front-end page, I would not have
been able to do that. So, we had to add
a database that actually um takes the
information. In in the case of my app, I
said, "Hey, I want to accept pictures
and I want to accept text. Let's keep
each of those things inside of a
database. So, inside of Replet, we
actually built that database. And let me
see if I can show that to you. Let me go
here.
Let's see if I can find my mouse.
Where's my mouse at?
I can't even see my mouse.
All right, maybe I won't.
All right, there we go. If I pop out of
here. All right, so the database in
here.
There it is.
If we go to tools
and we go to database here,
you can see that we've got a development
database for when we're testing
pre-publish. And then after we press
publish on our application, we've got
what's called a development or a
production database as well. So all of
the pictures that you guys uh put into
our wall are put into this database and
all the comments that were associated
with that are also put into this
database. If I go over to all databases
and go into the development database,
you see that I've got a different number
of rows. I've got 22 rows as opposed to
the 32 or 33. So the difference between
doing something locally before you
publish and then publishing it, it's
live to the world development versus
production.
All right,
let's see if I can come back to
here now.
All right, I'll just drag this over.
All right, so um after the database
publish adding APIs. So, if we wanted to
use one of those third-party services,
uh, typically you can do stuff like
weather, you can do stuff like time
series stock information, you can do
stuff like um you can literally pull
Shopify information or pull uh
information from any of your favorite
services into your Replet app such that
every time it loads up, it's pulling the
information that you want presented into
the actual uh interface. We've got
plenty of APIs that you can connect
with. Uh the shortest line in this whole
presentation that will allow you to do
something cool is add Replet off to my
app. If you do that, you're going to add
a portal basically for folks to log into
that'll look a little bit like um this.
You know, you can have Google, you can
have Apple, you can have any of the
typical ways that people log into
applications. Uh took like it takes like
five or six words to add authentication.
um so that users can kind of log their
session information, log their pictures,
log their text and um very easy to do
and implement. And a couple of words on
on user testing and research are in
here. Um when we get past the technical
hurdle, there are students that are
going to be marching towards um actually
experimenting in markets and seeing if
app A is better than app B and actually
capturing that market. So, I'm excited
to I'll tell you this last story as we
wrap. There's this student from Penn
State. Uh, he had three colleagues. So,
the four of them visited the Replet
offices. They said, "Hey, we um we
graduated recently and we're kind of
building the business, continuing to
build the businesses that we started in
college." I said, "Oh, that's cool."
Like, um, so each of you like did
businesses in college and like attended
classes. And the guy said, "Oh, kind
of." So he said one of us out of the
group for every class was like the
leader. So one of us would go to that
class, learn all the things, and then
come back and teach the rest of the
group. They would take four classes per
semester, and each of them would be the
leader. I said, "What do you do with all
of the extra time that you like in the
other three classes?" They're like, "Oh,
we we built businesses." So they built
four different businesses uh in the span
of four years. I said, "Oh, like you
make any money?" He's like, "Yeah, yeah,
yeah." Uh I said, "Like what? Five
figures? Like a couple grand?" He's
like, "No, each of us made like uh a
million dollars each over four years in
ARR for the businesses that we started."
So, I started to think about, oh, maybe
like instead of GPA, transcript, resume,
the idea that you could learn
information and monetize and like
participate in the economy with that
information across four years such that
you walk across the stage with zero debt
at the end of your college experience.
Maybe that should be like a goal that I
have for like the education team and
like part of the message that we talk to
uh teachers and faculty and other
students about um thumbs up if you think
that that's a reasonable idea. That
sound I I would I think I would hire
those those people to uh to join my
team. Entrepreneurial bootstrapping uh
scrappy about about these things. So
anyway, um the idea of multiple people
uh using one workspace to accelerate the
buildout time. Uh I'll send you all
these slides as well as we're coming. I
only got three minutes left. But um I'll
end with some limitations of Vive
coding. Uh the idea that you do need to
know a little bit about how product
building works in order to figure this
stuff out. A lot of the times you'll get
errors that are unfamiliar to you. So
the idea that you can screenshot that in
Replet and drag it into the interface
and say, "Hey, I don't know what this
actually is and how to fix it." The same
tool that you're using to build out your
application is the same replet agent
that you can ask questions to in order
to get unblocked and unlocked so that
you don't have to wait until a human
being can help you. You can literally
use a replet agent um to get unstuck and
build at the same time. Um,
in terms of complexity and technical
debt, I think
debugging is probably the most useful
skill on this list. And learning how to
do that if you're not technical is a lot
of trial and error and is a lot of time
you'll spend with agent learning the
things that uh traditional engineers and
traditional um, you know, folks in
computer science uh, learn in in in
class. All right. um vibe coding when it
needs guard rails. We typically
talk to technical people about some of
these things. But what I'll say is like
security, there's security scans before
you publish and then there's uh
validations and things that you should
know from a user interface perspective
like what's appropriate and what's not.
Uh we on a platform side do as much as
we can from a replet perspective to
protect the users and to protect the
builders. Uh but there's some common
sense and some things that you also uh
have a little bit of responsibility for
as well. Um with that I'll just say
thank you for your time and attention.
Um I appreciate all of your ears and are
excited to uh communicate and
collaborate with some of you if any of
these ideas resonate uh resonate. Thank
you guys so much.
All right.
>> Get these out.
>> Give them away.
>> Okay. All right. You want
>> There you go.
>> All right. Thank you, Brandon. So, we're
going to start back up our talks and our
first one we have is Peter Rathy with
Neo4j. You want to come up front, Peter?
Yeah.
>> What's that?
>> Phillip. Sorry. Did I say Peter?
>> Philip Rafy. [laughter]
>> All right.
I'm gonna try this mic out. Okay. That's
pretty pretty good.
>> Cool. Great to be here. Um, you've
probably heard a lot about things like
knowledge, context, semantics, memory,
ontology in AI these days. They're all
separate topics in a way, but I'm going
to bring them all together actually with
this topic around the knowledge layer.
And this comes out of working with
thousands of customers over the last few
years and seeing that there are a number
of different patterns uh in which they
take all those things and use them in
one common way.
And that pattern is the enterprise
knowledge layer. So here you can see a
simple picture of apps, agents, tools
accessing a knowledge layer that gives
agents what they need from a from a data
and knowledge perspective
and it it brings together data from
across the enterprise across you can see
on the bottom right all the different
operational data sources and on the
bottom left from the different um
analytic data sources. And now this
isn't a lift and shift. Uh the knowledge
knowledge distinct from data doesn't
mean everything about everything. It
means let's pull up the signal from the
noise and let's connect it up. Those
connections are are essential here. And
then likewise, you can start small and
then build up. So it's also very
incremental.
And if I look at the function, what's it
doing? It's storing structure, context,
and meaning.
It's providing uniform memory and
retrieval layer for agents. It also
bridges human and machine understanding.
And this comes back to this idea of
neurosymbolic AI, which is not new. It's
a few decades old, but it's coming back
with graphs in this different way of,
you know, you try to introspect a model
or introspect a vector database and, you
know, those are unintelligible to a
human being. Whereas with a graph, you
can really understand as a human what's
going on and then you can execute it um
as a machine and then it links and
unifies your data sources and objects
and stores data as a graph. Here
are a few examples of this in action.
So, one is Walmart's people AI knowledge
graph and graph application. This is an
agentic application usable by Walmart's
1.6 million or so employees that helps
them navigate their career journey. So,
what does the graph look like? It's all
the people, the reporting structure, the
history of the reporting structure,
their skills, how those have accumulated
over time, what projects they've been
on, what all the different open jobs
are, and what their job requirements
are. And it turns out that if you put
those all into one graph, you can
recommend someone's career journey
simply by connecting the dots. It's
almost like solving for HR by degrees of
Kevin Bacon. Um, and importantly,
this then feeds a model. So there's a
model in between the human and the
graph. But the questions actually can be
answered either by the model by feeding
it more context or you can actually get
an answer from the graph and run it
deterministically. So you have this
powerful optionality of running um
deterministically or
nondeterministically.
Here's another example at Uber who has a
different kind of graph. It's the rules
graph. So Uber operates in 15,000
cities. they have different offerings in
those cities. Those are called different
things. There are different laws,
regulations as well as um Uber's own
reasons for varying the offerings.
And those rules are stored and executed
in the graph. And I brought one more
example from a major gaming company.
This is one of the largest gaming
companies in the world where you can see
uh an API conversational AI accessing an
API layer accessing a multi- aent system
and then using the graph [music] as a
semantic layer and semantic layer here
means taking business terms and concepts
the relationships between those and then
mapping those to physical infrastructure
and down to data infrastructure and
where you can find the data. So agents
use the graph to get a map of where to
go in the enterprise to find data. So
these are three different kinds of
graphs and you could say this is
semantics and ontology earlier was the
domain graph. You have a rules graph
which is a form of memory procedural
memory.
And what they have in common and the key
core insight that's behind why these
people chose to build the systems in
this particular way is that they saw
that their data either showed up as a
network. So in the real and digital
world that AI needs to engage with. It
tends to show up in a few ways. Can show
up as a network. Computers areworked,
social networks, communications,
biology, ecology, transportation and so
on. or is a hierarchy like the Walmart
HR example which is actually multiple
hierarchies and journeys and and then
likewise with customer journey, patient
journey and the like
and so if you can choose to represent
those in tables and in fact that's been
the dominant way over the last few
decades
but there's a newer way to look at data
which in fact as of two years ago is an
ISO standard. So for those of you who
might not be familiar with this, for the
first time in nearly 40 years, the
International Standards Organization
blessed a new data model in the database
space uh the property graph data model
that represents data like this, the way
we're talking about for dealing with
data that shows up in the real and
digital worlds as networks, hierarchies,
and paths.
Now, why do you need a new model? Why
isn't it enough to deal with what you've
got? Well, let's look at what you've
got.
You can use a foundation model, but
they've been trained on the world's
data, not on yours. Okay. Well, then I
can train my own small model, but that's
expensive. And then let's say I get over
that. The minute I train the model, it's
already out of date. And then everything
I've trained my model on becomes fair
game for answering any decision by any
agent for any purpose. Um, and we know
that you have all kinds of rules around
access controls inside of an enterprise.
It can also still hallucinate and lack
discernment.
Um, and it's a black box. Data struct
structured as static rows and columns is
great. That's where most data is. And
that's good for answering fixed and
simple questions. But if my questions
get super intricate and complex and I
don't know what in advance what the next
question is going to be, then actually
this is where graphs have always shined.
I've been doing this for more than more
than a decade and this has been the main
reason for using graph technology.
Now I can look at other unstructured
forms of data but that tends to be
difficult to mine and make sense of and
as I pointed out earlier vectors are
completely opaque and it's arguably like
a one or two trick pony and then
organizational data is spread across
silos. So how do I bring the knowledge
from across the silo so that my agents
can share the intelligence of the entire
company not just what's in one system?
Now many companies have been doing this
to the point where Gartner's gone out
and said look this is a clear trend and
their recommendation to data and
analytics leaders is they must redesign
the data and analytics architecture to
make the context layer the central brain
for AI agents to deliver trusted
intelligence. That's exactly what we're
talking about here.
Um, now look at let's look at the
requirement agents have of knowledge.
Now agents
are highly interactive. So they can't
just interact with a like a data lake or
a lakehouse. They need a real-time
system where they can have um low
latency retrievalss as well as update
the system so you can have a virtuous
cycle of self improvement.
You also need to be able to store
structured, unstructured and
semistructured data. Number two. Number
three, you need to bring together data
from across the silos. Now your data
lakes and lakehouses bring data together
from across the silos but at the expense
of losing the connections between them.
You're centralizing everything but
you're not connecting it.
Um you need to be able to have a rag
corpus and I would add a graph rag
corpus.
And then you also need data access
controls for exactly the reasons we were
talking about earlier corporate firewall
security privacy.
So this is what agents need. Now, if I
bring all that together, this actually
answers all of that. This is really a
zoom in of what we went into earlier.
And at the highest level, you've got
your data that's connected as a graph,
your domain data, and that can be your
own domain. Um, that can be reference
data that you get in from third parties.
And then you also have the option these
days of running graph queries against
data lakes through technologies like
Neoforj virtually. So virtual graph is
on there
in in the ontology bucket. Uh I include
the semantic layer. So this is
everything around meaning your business
meaning and then how it maps to where
your data is located. This is like a a
business in a techn technology map. And
then last but not least is memory. So
um conversational memory is just all the
different texts and prompts. But then
much like the human brain as part of the
sleep process of sleeping and memory
consolidation gives you long-term memory
which is what are the things that matter
and how do they connect. Um long-term
memory tends to be best stored as a
graph. Procedural memory tends to be
best stored as a graph. Context and
decision traces which is another form of
memory. Likewise um
so what's the role of knowledge layer?
This is a whole presentation that I've
rolled up into one slide um because
we've just got a short amount of time.
I've got some learning resources at the
end. But number one is providing context
for agents for better answers. I'll show
you a link to a paper that just came out
um by the UK's uh center for uh data and
AI innovation that um uh
complex uh let's say a rich academic
piece of research that shows that you
get substantially better I think it's uh
more than twice as many questions are
answered versus not with 80% better
fidelity lower hallucinations and um
fewer tokens. So very very powerful. It
can connect the silos. It can give you
knowledge transparency and an option for
deterministic processing. Um it can
respect um data access controls. And
then surprisingly to me it can handle
complex questions much better. We I've
had customer after customer come back
and tell me that AI models do a much
better job of answering a complex
question expressed as human language
using graph queries than using a
relational query. And that's because the
graph query language GQL or cipher you
might you might express a complex
question as in five lines that's 200
lines in SQL. It's a much more tur
representation that's nearer to human
language.
Now what are the kinds of data
concretely in the enterprise? There are
two ways you could look at this. One is
let's say a breadth first or top down
view is the enterprise itself is a
connected organism. So you can build a
map connecting up the silos.
The other one is bottoms up. Here you
can see you have the product graph which
is a product hierarchy. Um and out of
that you you have all these different
use cases underneath that are supported.
recommendations,
um, product pricing, inventory, but then
that connects, if you connect that into
the supplier data, you can do supply
chain optimization and so on and so so
for so forth. We saw the employee graph,
career journey, etc., etc. And you can
build these out incrementally. I don't
have a lot of time to go through this,
but I'll just flash it. Is um, this
looks at the top AI use cases. just
looking at data coming out of the top
systems integrators um and uh and and
and some of the top AI labs um mapped to
the kinds of graphs that show up mapped
to the kinds of AI motions and process
that are enabled and you'll see things
like multihop reasoning um and agentic
workflows in there. So drilling into
reasoning,
one takeaway I'd like to leave you with
for today is that the knowledge layer
isn't just a passive place where you
store information. Um it can actually do
various forms of computation. So I'm
running short on time and I'm going to
zoom through these but graph querying
which is different forms of pattern
matching and filtering. Graph algorithms
clustering link prediction and so on.
similarity in search, GNN's which it is
a topological vector um another kind of
vector and then graph visualization
and then the key advantages here are
graph rag which gives you improvements
in accuracy multihop reasoning which
helps agents perform more complex tasks
um semantic maps uh map of the
enterprise decision traces which is a
whole talk in itself I'll give you some
breadcrumbs and and memory. So I'll just
leave you with with a few resources and
then we'll drop. One is I wrote this
piece two years ago. It still holds up.
Um introducing graph rag.
Next one just was published two weeks
ago describing the enterprise knowledge
layer. So it's a kind of a pros
description of this talk.
Number three is this paper that I just
mentioned um showing that uh agents
using graph rag versus vector only are
80% more truthful, answer twice as many
questions, hallucinate less, and then
it's less expensive. You use far fewer
tokens.
And then last but not least, if you uh
grab this QR code, we've prepared a
special um landing page for all of you
with some further learning resources.
Um, one of them is, uh, Andrew Ing was
here today. Um, there are some deep
learning.ai courses and then Neoforj has
her own graph academy with lots of
learning there. So, I'll leave you with
that. Thank you. Looks like I'm just on
time and uh, thanks and I'll encourage
you to go and find your own graph.
All right. Thank you, Phillip.
>> Uh, next up we have Josh Alrech. You
come up with Imbu. Welcome.
>> Yes.
Is this the Where's the button? This is
the
>> Thank you. Great.
Okay. Uh, today we're going to talk
about the importance of building open
software and building punk software. Uh,
a lot of the talks we've seen have been
about all these really cool platforms
and everything. That's great, but it
turns out you can build pretty much
whatever you want yourself. So, that's
what we're going to be talking about
today. I really like this quote as a
place to start. So it's this present
moment used to be the unimaginable
future. And this is by Stuart Brand from
the Long Now Foundation. I think if you
went back five years and you asked
people or you told people what we could
do today with coding agents, they'd be
like, "What are you talking about?
There's no way that's going to happen."
So things have come super far. And we
have AI agents that let us think and
dream and create, you know, the
unimaginable future that will come in 5
years from today. Uh but today Frontier
AI is fully controlled by a few
corporations
and there are plenty of hypothetical
dangers. For example, what if an AI
company released a model like Fable and
then unreleased that model? Or what if
they increase the price dramatically? Or
what if they ban your account? Or what
if they change the terms of service so
you can't do the same thing you were
doing like say AI research? Like can
your business survive those events? Can
the thing you're working on, the thing
you care about survive them just
disappearing on you? Uh, but these
dangers are not actually hypothetical
anymore. Like the largest AI labs today
are now routinely hiding the thoughts of
their AI agents, hiding the logits,
making it harder to do third party
audits, hacking into your website as we
saw a week or two ago, refusing to help
you fix vulnerabilities by refusing to
work on cyber security defense, silently
degrading performance as we saw from
Anthropic a few weeks ago. uh competing
with your business as we see from
anthropic making their own drugs after
partnering with people or making their
own claude code design after partnering
with Figma or banning your account with
no recourse. So there is an existential
risk from AI to you not to the human
race. We're not about to go extinct but
your business and livelihood that could.
So I think that if we want a good future
our thoughts and our agents thoughts
need to be fully under our control. This
can't be something that we rely on a
third-party
remote computer to provide and that can
be turned off at any time if this is how
we're thinking. If we're using this
stuff for education, for building our
own tools that we run our lives and our
businesses on, we can't have something
where it's not actually part of us. So,
how do we do that? I think we need to do
that by making the whole stack open. So,
it's time for a free software revolution
to take back control. And that's what
Punk Software is about. It's a software
uprising.
So, what is punk software? Well, it's a
term that we randomly made up when some
people DM'd us on Twitter and was like,
"Oh, I love your punk software stuff."
It's like, "Okay, cool. That that's
great. Like, let's take that. Let's run
with it." By punk, we mean
decentralized, minimal, DIY. It's more
of an ethos or a vibe. It's a way of
thinking about software. The original
punk, you know, music movement was very
much about doing things yourself, right?
Being bad at playing musical
instruments, being bad at writing code.
That's fine. We want to take that ethos
and apply that to software. By punk
software, we means software you build
yourself. You can share it. You can help
other people build it. It's meant to be
something that you understand, you can
explore, you can create, and it's yours.
So, what makes good punk software? Well,
I think there's five things. One, it's
individual. So by this I mean it's
something that is both controlled by
you, fully controlled by you, fully a
part of you, but also something that you
can customize and make more yours. Can
you control everything about it? Today
there's so much open source software
that this is possible. Uh we also want
it to be decentralized. So it's not just
something that can easily be turned off.
It's not something that runs on someone
else's server. It's something that is
everywhere. It's diffuse. It's that's
really what we mean by democratization
and by empowering people is literally
you having tools that are yours to allow
you to do what you want to do. Three, we
want this stuff to be open. So we want
software to be something not just that's
open source where you can read the code
or not just open weights but open in the
sense of you can actually look at what
is happening inside of the model, inside
of your system, inside of your operating
system and understand what's going on.
You can learn, you can educate yourself
and you can build larger systems outside
of that. Now, another side benefit of it
being open is that the agent can look at
it too. And this turns out to be
extremely useful for making much more
useful systems.
We also want this to be anti-
monopolistic. And by this I mean making
tools that
fight against centralized power and try
and make individual people in control of
their technology and their lives. We
don't want a place where all of our data
is locked in some silo that we don't
have access to. We don't want a place
where suddenly the prices can go up and
we can't do anything about it. And
finally, we want to make moral software.
So, I think people have forgotten a
little bit that the point of software is
to do things in the real world.
Recursive self-improvement is all fine
and good, but at the end of the day,
what are we improving at? We want to
make things that are good for us, are
good for the world. And so, there's a
moral component to punk software as
well.
So what does this look like in practice?
Well, in practice, there's a lot of
stuff that goes into making these like
agentic AI applications and systems. So
there's a whole set of stacks and we
want open everything. So starting at the
very bottom, we want open
infrastructure, things like Linux,
things like Docker, things like SSH. We
have a huge rich ecosystem of open
source software to pull from. We want
open source inference. We also want open
source models, things like GLM or
DeepSeek or things like Neotron or
Inkling. We also want open source
harnesses, things like Codex, Open Code,
Klein, Goose. We want as well the next
layers that go above these. So, how do
we coordinate those harnesses? How do we
coordinate agents? Things like T-Mox and
Herder and CMU are ways of playing with
multiple agents and getting them to
communicate and coordinate and building
larger uh systems out of these smaller
components. And finally, we want top
level things that use these agents to do
something useful at the end of the day.
So today we're going to look at three
uh that we are currently working on at
imbue. So the bottom two are called
manager and then a specific plug-in for
manager called manager donate. And the
third one is an application that we're
building called mines. Manager is an
open source tool that you can use to
coordinate agents that's available free
today. It's online. It's on GitHub.
Manager donate and mines are two things
that are still in beta. So if you want
access just email us we'll happily send
it on send it over. In fact they're
technically open. You can go find them
but it'll make more sense if you email
us. Okay. So the first one manager. So
the point of manager is to commoditize
the AI models and compute providers. So
by this I mean make it so that you can
use any AI model you want and any
compute provider you want.
The core idea is to make AI agents into
a building block for larger systems. If
you can get them to do whole tasks for
you, then you can build up a larger
system that doesn't tie you to just
codecs or just cloud code. So the idea
with manager is to stop requiring AI
agents to be interactive. We don't want
you sitting there hitting yes, it looks
fine to run this gigantic bash command.
I guess like that's kind of a waste of
your time. You want to be thinking about
how to run these things in ways that
compose and build up larger systems. So
here's a kind of overview of what
manager is and how it works. So it's a
thin layer that sits in between your
application and any harness and any
compute provider. So you can use codeex,
quad code, whatever. You can use AWS or
GCP whatever. But the point is you don't
have to think about that. Instead you
just have a very simple command line
tool where you can say manager create
and launch an agent or you can tell it
exactly where to launch it or you can
tell it you can give it a name or you
can tell it what harness to use. You can
still pass in extra arguments you know
the second to last one there model
create tell it exactly to use opus uh or
you can send it a message. So the point
of manager really is that you have these
other
primitives as well. So you can use
something like manager message to send a
message to the agent or you can use
manager transcript to see the messages
that have already been sent both from
you and from the agent and this is
unified access across the different
coding agents. So instead of you having
to worry about like oh like the format
for codeex and the format for cloud code
are different. You don't have to worry
about that. Manager takes care of this
sort of layer of interoperability. The
same thing for compute. You also have
things like manager list to see your
agents. Manager connect to connect
directly to one. When you call that you
just end up right in the terminal
running as if you were running cloud
code natively. But that cloud code might
be running on AWS or on modal or
locally. It doesn't matter. You get to
interact with it. Send it on its way.
disconnect and you're all set. You have
things like manager weight uh to compose
other larger things, manager snapshot,
it just is a big toolkit that allows you
to make these higher level systems.
There are many more commands. You can go
online and see the rest yourself. So if
we score this on in terms of punk
software like is this good punk
software? I think so. I mean that that's
why I made it this way. Uh so is it
individual? Yes. One of the things
that's different about manager is
there's no service. We're not trying to
sell you a SAS thing. There's no remote
database. Everything is local. It simply
asks every time you run it, are there
any things in AWS? Is there anything
local? Okay, great. So, you can control
everything about this. It's easy to make
plugins, change the settings. It's all
just directly controlled by you. So,
it's fully decentralized, completely
yours. It's MIT licensed. Uh the point I
think is relatively anti- monopolistic
and that it's trying to commoditize AI
models and compute providers. It's
trying to make it so you're not locked
into their sort of vertical ecosystems.
and it has at least a little bit of a
moral character and that like is trying
to directly empower you as an
individual. Okay. Second uh thing that
we'll look at today is a plug-in for
manager. This is called manager donate.
It's very easy to make new plugins. This
particular plugin we're making to make
it easy to donate your extra tokens to
science. So the problem that we're
solving here is that you don't fully
utilize your subscription. In theory,
your subscription gives you like a maybe
a I think it's about like a $100
subscription per month for Cloud Code.
If you max it out, gives you about
$4,000 on the API. But you don't always
max it out. But if you come to the end
of the week and you haven't maxed it
out, like why not give those tokens to a
scientist who would happily do some
useful work. So that's what this allows
us to do. And it's built on top of
Manager, which makes it easy for the
actual implementation. So manager can
run the tasks from the scientist in a
sandbox for you or in a local docker
container. So you don't need to worry
about them running untrusted code. It
also can run can understand the usage
from your subscription. So you can make
sure that it doesn't use tokens that you
were actually going to use yourself.
So scoring this on you know punk
software how punk is this? I mean it's
fully individual. You can control
exactly how much you want to donate, how
much you don't want to donate, which
causes you want to donate to etc. It's
fully decentralized. The idea is that
scientists will be able to just post
whatever research they want done. Your
system will go off and pull that,
compute it, send it back. Uh it's
completely open source. Uh anti-
monopolistic a little bit, I guess. I
don't know how many monopolies there are
that are, you know, doing open source
distributed AI science. Uh and moral,
yeah, I mean contributing to science, I
think most of us probably feel is a good
thing. So the third thing we're going to
look at is the application that we're
building on top of manager that's more
for regular people than for software
engineers. So minds is an application
that's meant to be personal intelligence
sort of like a personal computer. The
core idea is that you run the language
model alongside the software that it
creates. So instead of creating an
application like in replet and then
deploying it and you have a database and
you have production, you have
migrations, that's just a bunch of
noise. That's a bunch of extra
complexity that you don't need when
you're trying to make a personal
dashboard or a little script that runs
every day. So the idea is to build on
top of manager, make it easy for people
to run these things in a fully open
source way that's completely under their
control. So at its core, it's about
running a little virtual machine either
on your computer or remotely inside of
this machine manager coordinates the
coding agents and uses them to make the
different applications. These
applications are whatever you want. You
can have it go do one-off tasks. You can
have it triage your inbox. You can have
it rank science fiction short stories
that it thinks you would like. whatever
you want but the point of manager is to
abstract across you know where is this
running what compute provider what AI
provider is is is doing this thing so
that the thing is fully under your
control if this thing if you want to
tell it to like you know ask questions
about Tanaman Square or you want to ask
questions about cyber security it'll
flip between the models to make sure
that both of those get answered so if we
think okay how punk is this the reason
that we made this is to make a sort of
individualized
uh way of making coding agents. So, it's
completely under your control. It's
completely decentralized. It's
completely open source. Uh, and it's
meant to not lock you into a vertical
system like cloud code, co-work, etc.
So, uh, I think it'd be great to have
you join the revolution. Help us make
punk software, make the whole stack
open. We saw some examples. Uh, and if
you want, uh, feel free to get involved
by, uh, looking at this QR code. If you
want to donate your tokens to science,
if you want people to give you tokens
for doing your own science, if you want
us to highlight the punk software that
you've made, if you want to join our
punk software hack nights or join our
Slack or try out Mines or any of our
products, please just email me. We'll
happily connect uh and would love to
build the stuff together.
All right. Thank you, Josh. Next up, we
have Su um Wusak Quan with Infirect.
Forwards and backwards.
>> Okay.
I'm I'm uh sorry I'm sorry for this but
can sorry can I get the speaker notes
uh it's not presented here
can can I increase the phone size please
Okay. Yeah. Uh, sorry for the delay. Hi
everyone. Uh, thanks for joining today.
I'm Usok. I'm a co-creator of VLM and
also a co-founder of Infact, a startup
built around VLM. Today I wanted to talk
about like what agents demand for the
inference stack and uh how we evolving
VLM like open source inference stack to
meet these demands. Uh let's get
started.
So key intro for everyone new uh like
EDLM VLM is an open source EDLM
inference engine to make EDLM inference
like efficient and effortless. It
started about three years ago here at UC
Berkeley during my PhD and has been
growing rapidly ever since like even now
and we hit it like 88k GitHub stars I
think pretty recently. Uh importantly
this this is a very highly collaborative
project across academia and industry
with major contributors including
Redhead, Nvidia, AMD, Google like
Moonshot and uh outside inferact and
it's also being widely deployed in
industry for production inference.
Uh there are two main ways to use VLM.
I'll go very quickly. The first is the
EDLM class which is a Python interface
for offline Python interface for offline
batch inference. You give you give it a
hugging face model name and you call the
generate and that's it. So VLM
automatically handles model loading,
optimization,
uh scheduling and memory management
under the hood so that you don't need to
care about it in utilizing GPUs and it
generates a text completion uh of the
prompts and returns to you.
The second is online serving VLM serve.
uh this is a single comment uh uh that
you can get a like OpenAI compatible
endpoint from uh like and obviously we
also support anthropic APIs too any
agent framework that speaks the agent
the the open AAI or entropic API can
also like work out of the box uh since
yeah the API layer is pretty standard
uh so that's how you use VLM uh in the
first place but as you can see the agent
the API itself is pretty much similar to
the the few years ago, right? Like so it
actually didn't really change that much
for for agents. What has changed a lot
for agent is everything underneath it.
So yeah specifically like uh at a higher
level agents change the inference
problem along three axis like first is
like large models right the frontier
agent models like Kimmy K3 like deep 4
are like trillion parameters
and like that forces all to get serious
about like model parallelisms. uh
basically like it gave us a lot of like
opportunities for us to like paralyze
the model in many creative ways with
different trade-offs. I'll talk about it
in more detail later. A second is long
context, right? Like agent sessions run
for like hundreds of turns like up to a
million tokens and the context only
grows over a session.
So like managing KV cache of these like
uh the previous turns is very very uh
very important for like inference
performance and we definitely need to
ensure that like any like uh we're not
the inference framework is not
recomputing any of the tokens in the
previous turn because otherwise you'll
be like a lot of recmp computation and
like a lot of waste of compute.
A third is enormous token demand like
now that like agents are getting really
really smart and so capable uh so that
like there are actually now near
infinite demand now near infinite places
to to deploy it so the demand is
effectively unbounded. Uh it's it's
growing faster than than the GPU supply.
So like so the the inference engine and
inference serving has to adapt to it. uh
and our solution to this is to basically
like enable this efficient inference for
more diverse like uh hardware backends
so that we can utilize all available
compute to generate tokens.
Okay, let's get into more details.
Uh yeah, let's start with parallelism.
So to efficiently serve such large
models like VLM today supports seven
like mainly seven different types of
parallelism
uh like including tensor pipeline data
expert like sequence parallelism and
like two different kinds of context
parallelism you may recognize some of
those in the from the training world
like VLM supports them all and uh plus
the ones that don't exist in the
training like decode context parallelism
which is parallelism around the KV cache
as a general purpose engine like VM
efficiently implements all of these
parallelism and also like mixture of
them right
however like we found that that's not
enough the important thing is that like
uh these need these parallelism need to
be properly selected and tuned like for
the target model architecture the target
cluster setup and also the the target
workload shape there's no universal
winner or there's universal solution. Uh
let me show you what this tuning looks
like in a for a real model.
So uh this is like deepse pro uh like
running prefill of it like on B200 GPUs
uh in the disagregated serving setup
like so these set of GPUs only do only
perform prefill.
uh basically the the most
straightforward way to deploy the model
like deepc model for like prefield on
this GPU cluster is just using like
eightway tensor parallelism that's the
most standard and like like simplest way
to do it however the winning
configuration is pretty much different
like it's a like in in this like
particular workload setup like it was a
like two-way tensor parallel times like
eightway two-way pipeline parallel times
eight way uh So like tensor parallel
plus sequence parallelism and accessor
parallelism like uh deployed uh across
16 GPUs for each model replica.
So like and like we found that this this
gets like much lower TTFP basically like
the latency on the first token and also
much higher like throughput per GPU uh
compared to this the straightforward uh
like single host eightway TP baseline.
The reason being is yeah like it's it's
actually pretty much complicated so I'm
not going to much details but the reason
being is like pipeline parallelism is
like enabling the parallelism between
different chunks in the long prefill
sequence parallelism enables more
communication and computation overlap
and expert parallelism gives us better
gem shapes better matrix multiplication
shapes compared to the uh like eightway
tensor parallelism. Yeah, the so the
high the the the takeway is that
basically there's no winner and also
like yeah this like we need to basically
this models makes this kind of like
model parallelism and sharding a
necessity and there are many different
ways to do it and like depending on how
you choose and like tune the these like
parallelism degree like the performance
like better like varies a lot and
basically in the in this agency work in
this agency era we need to you need to
have the right like insight and
performance model to set the uh to to
configure this in the correct way and VM
basically provides the the common
substrate that you can basically play
with all these different parallelism.
So the second is uh like KV cache. Uh so
speaking of it so like the one very
critical critical characteristic of the
modern Ed lens are that they are
basically hybrid models like they are
like basically hybrid in the sense that
they're interlion
with some other more efficient attention
mechanisms like sighting window or like
linear attention such as Kim delta
attention and and this is basically the
the thing that makes the the 1 million
context lengths feasible because global
attention itself is is like takes too
much memory like if you want to really
go to 1 million context. Uh however in
theory this is very efficient. Uh but
like this in practice this creates a lot
of like real systems challenge like
basically these layers uh like with
different attention types have
completely different memory behavior
like full attention like the KV cache of
full attention grows linearly with the
context while like linear attention like
KDA like keeps a fixed size state per
sequence uh or so I mean like regardless
of the the actual context lengths. So
like how should we curve up the GPU
memory between them is the is the real
six uh one of the like uh important
systems question.
The straightforward like solution or
answer to this question is static
partitioning like reserve like uh like x
percentage for like uh full attention y
percentage for the rest things like
that. Uh this is this works but the
problem is that like the the optimal
split between the two depends on the
batch size and context lengths which is
pretty dynamic over time during
inference.
Uh so like the solution in VLM is
dynamic partitioning. So which is
basically using one shared memory pool
for GPU memory. Uh and each attention
type with different memory behavior like
uh gets its own allocator uh drawing
from the shared memory pool. Um so yeah
like in a sense the full attention
allocator like yeah like reccast to this
shared memory pool on the specific
number of tokens while in the the KDA
allocator because it's a linear
attention like allocates the one giant
block for the entire sequence and like
we have a logic to uh to dynamically
share the same memory space uh between
the two. Uh yeah this is also pretty
much detail so I'm not going to uh too
deep but basically this uh this is one
like critical feature in VLM that's uh
like allows you to not worried about how
to handle the different types of
attention and the the memory split
between the and the and like VM
basically automatically rebalances the
memory space between the two so that
like no GPU memory is wasted.
Okay. Uh yeah, regarding KV cache though
also another thing is that like
important uh thing is uh like managing
this KV cache within the the GPU GPU
memory space isn't enough right like
especially the agent sessions are pretty
long live and also very intermittent uh
which means basically the the model
generates and then generate some upper
tokens and then waits right like for two
calls or sometimes for human response
and then like it basically continues and
during those weights the KB cache is uh
is somehow stored in some some area
right like it could be stored in GPU
memory it could be stored in some other
memory right like uh to store in to
store this KV cache uh unused uh at the
moment uh we basically use uh uh this uh
like concept of KV connector this is
basically allows to leave this like idle
KV cache I like store this idle KV cache
to external memory like CPU memory or
disk uh and bring it back when it's
needed and uh yeah like here basically
we yeah like uh yeah truly speaking like
basically we did uh a lot of efforts to
design this abstraction and make sure it
is well working with third party
libraries like moon key and also it is
well working with like other KV transfer
mechanism like like prefill
disagregation In the prefill disegration
case, the KV uh the movement of KV cache
is pretty dynamic and complex because it
needs to move between prefill instance
to decode instance, prefill instance to
the uh to the distributed KV storage
pool like Moon Cake and things like
that. And we basically like set up the
the infra to to to efficiently handle
this. So that like again in the in the
many turn like agent sessions we never
recomputee like yeah as long as the
storage allows like we never recomputee
the the tokens in the previous case in
the previous turns.
Okay. Uh the last part is like hardware.
Uh so basically we believe the economics
of tokens have kind of is flipping. Uh
so like as models get smarter and more
intelligent the value of a token uh like
far exists the cost of generating it. So
therefore naturally the demand is
exploding and we we're witnessing that
uh and honestly there are not enough uh
GPUs in the world to serve it. So the
question becomes uh can we use all the
available compute on earth to generate
tokens efficiently? Yeah. And and VLM
basically like trying to aims to uh
answer that question to achieve the goal
like we support more than like 10
hardware backends today. like obviously
like Nvidia GPU is like our major focus
but we also uh work on like Google TPU,
AMD GPU and like many other hardware uh
chips from the uh from the industry uh
and they basically have like the plug-in
structure to VLM to share the core part
of VLM while they're customizing some
some specific parts for their hardware
backends.
And yeah, like obviously this this makes
more sense because like yeah the the API
in the inference space is pretty much
standardized right you can still use the
same like open AI or anthropic API and
uh just that with different hardware
under the hood generating the tokens
uh yeah like for the for the sake of
time I'll probably need to skip this
slides but basically yeah we got a lot
of lessons from like supporting this
hardware and we're actively working on
it but like the TLDDR is that like like
bringing up this new hardware and making
it efficiently supporting the new models
is uh is I think getting better because
of coding agents. Uh but on the on the
other side it also still requires a
pretty like retaking the entire
inference stack from ground up. So yeah
like we are actively working on it.
Yeah. And for a summary, yeah, like uh
in the agentic era basically stresses
the inference on three axis and VLM
answers each uh each of the one like
here large models with workload aware
model parallelism long context with a
dynamic and hierarchical KB cache and uh
like exploding token demand with diverse
hardware backends and everything I
showed you today is open source. So
please come join us uh with different
places. Thank you.
All right. Thank you, Wuk. So, next up
we have Banga Juke with Raex Arc.
Welcome.
Cool.
Uh, hi everyone. My name is Bonha. Uh,
I'm currently co-founder and CTO of
Regisart. Uh, before that I got also got
my PhD from Berkeley. So really excited
to u be back here. Uh, today I'm going
to introduce uh, Ashland mouse and where
we build the frontier AI infrastructure
uh, within Reddit.
And so the mission of Reddisart is to
make frontier level AI infrastructure
open and accessible to everyone. And to
achieve that we're building in open
source right now where our inference
engine and HGLN and is adopted as a
production inference engine uh all over
the places. And then our recent RF
framework MOS are also gradually picking
up as a production like frontier level
uh infra for post training.
A quick intro of HLN. So we view that as
a production grade open source inference
engine where Asha itself is supporting
language model and vision language model
inference and we also have a diffusion a
relatively newer project on image and
video generation and then including also
like V and wood model inference as well
and third more recently we have a omni
which is more targeted around ASR and
TTS model uh more around the audio side.
So altogether like the entire Ashland
ecosystem is more optimized for agentic
workloads. Uh and we provide really
performant day zero model support and
also very broad hardware support
including Nvidia, AMD, TPU, trrenium,
Intel and so on so forth.
We also have miles which is our enterp
enter enterprisegrade reinforcement
learning framework. So it's forked and
co-evolved with slime with more features
uh on Nvidia and AMD latest hardwares.
Uh slam is a project that uh like triple
AI built together uh with a community
for their uh GM model series training.
So it has been battle tested on
production training at very very large
scale and for miles we also provide day
zero support for all the open models uh
including Kim Jam like inkling from
syncing machine like neotron from avidia
etc. So at day zero when the model are
released you can just directly use mouse
for uh training and customization and
use a for inference. So mouse uh
natively use aan as a robot stage and
then use avidia's magnetron as a
training stage for the best performance
here.
So today Ashel and Miles are already
adopted widely by different enterprises
and writing start companies like all the
hardware companies all the hyperscalers
enterprises AI labs especially new labs
and also developer tools and new clouds
are mostly like widely adopting Ashland
mouse in their part of their
infrastructure for inference and
training.
There are also different ecosystem
collaboration where we work with uh
Google cloud uh very closely for
improving their throughput for uh their
internal inference stack and also
cloudfare IBM like XAI meta they all use
achelan uh as a back as a back end for
their inference engine.
So to us 2026 is actually the year of
agentic infrastructure. So for infer
side the demand is exploding and
actually the challenges are very unique
and for training side and actually every
detail matters and it's still early but
everything needs to be done right so
that you can train the model without
hurting its generalization capability.
So I briefly go over the challenges in
both inference side and training side
with the introduction of agentic use
cases. So for agentic inference um the
first thing people care about is high
cache reuse. Um people see Deepseek V4
has a really low like cache hit rate
price and such high cash reuse is
actually very important to uh ensure
that and also make sure uh you have
really high cash hit rate and to reduce
your entire cost of serving and second
thing is that people are now all moving
towards trillion number parameters and
models. So how do you handle those large
models is also bringing more and more
challenges to open source stack and of
course like for contest window right now
1 million contest is already the norm.
So there there will need to be more
optimization around super long context.
So how does Helen address those
challenges?
So first for uh high cache reuse uh
we're bringing like two unique
technology introduced by HLN. One is
unified hybrid radius cache which is
designed for all the recent hybrid
models where you can make sure the
preface cache uh will run smoothly with
all the hybrid models and new
architectures introduced recently. And
second is our high cache design and
system which basically enable people to
move the KV cache down from HBM to DAM
and even to your external storage so
that there will be most efficient way of
handling KV cache in between different
memory layers. So as a result um as an
concrete example of one qu three coder
uh we get to greatly improve like cache
rate and also QTFT and throughoot as
well.
The second challenge is large model
scaling when it comes to one trillion,
three trillion and even like and even
larger models. So the standard technique
definitely include all the 5D like
standard parallelism uh like data
paralism tensor context pipeline uh
export parallelism etc. There are also
like newer um parallelism strategy like
GPU attention like DCP and PCP as well.
And beyond that there are also new
combinations of deployment strategy like
people start from colllocate but then
gradually move towards like prefill
decode mode uh prefill decode
disagregation mode for a larger scale uh
and more imbalanced preferral decode
deployment. And now for vision language
model there also like EPD where you also
dis disagregate encoder in this case and
there are also different runtime
optimizations around SGLAN where um
there are different ways of supporting
spec decoding from eagle to MTP to D
flash and recent DSpark uh from
introduced by deepseek. There also like
scheduling um designs including the
overlapuler and then our most recent
spec v2 for better support uh the native
spec decoding u speed up in inference
stage.
And third and also like perhaps very
important context is also related to how
people handle long context especially
when it comes to scaling to up to 1
million parameter uh sorry one one
million context window. So the first one
u is chunk pipeline parallelism where we
get to essentially instead of sending
the whole prefill sequence at once we
get to chunk them and chunk the entire
long prompts into different smaller
chunks and then process them like um in
parallel. And the second thing is a
different dimension of chunking or
paralism where we split sentences or
sequences into across GPUs for long
contest handling. There also uh
specifically uh sparse attention uh
related optimization we did with high
high spars where we get to process a
full KV with a hot buffer here and then
to ensure those sparse attention get
more um uh get um basically occupy less
memory and result in much higher
throughput in this case.
So by combination of all the techniques
and also all the like fine-tuning uh we
did uh this is a very concrete example
where at state zero uh our GM 5 5 5.2
performance is already the best and then
over the time we already are able to
achieve like over 2.2x improvement and
achieving like up to 500 tokens per
second tokens per second per user in
this stage.
So in summary, Ashan has been um keeping
shaping the frontier capabilities and in
a fast verified and optimized fashion.
We're the first to introduce a lot of
new techniques in large production
including radius attention like spec
decoding PD desertation like sparse
attention and also native support with
smiles and later recently like D flash
the spark and high sparse as well.
So the next I'll briefly mention about
agentive training part. Um there are
also a lot more challenges introduced um
by long long context agentic training.
So one is that people now are looking at
much more diverse environments. So it's
not only about more tool calls and
longer context but also about some
environments might be very hard to
execute and it might be even requiring
like lab experiments to get the reward
signal. And the second is also about
train inference mismatch which is a very
popular topic in frontier labs these
days where if you have very large train
inference mismatch between different
engine then that will naturally and
silently turn your RL uh to be more off
policy and hurt your entire training
run.
And third is also people really care
about throughput in your entire use
cases as you if you have higher
throughput that means you essentially
get to iterate faster with your
different IO experiments and then you
get more utilization with your GPU as
well.
So to address the first challenge uh we
have been working very closely with most
of the uh environment suppliers and then
miles right now already natively support
most of the open source u environments
including hover like open in like prime
intellect verifiers and daytona and also
like nemo gym and also agent in which is
used by recent communic case post
training
for crackness uh this has been one of
the mile's um biggest focus to ensure
the train inference mismatch uh will be
eliminated. There are different ways to
reduce that. One is just to introduce
deterministic kernels in your inference
engine which is a like pre prerequest to
actually ensure zero kale for the
inference and train engine to make sure
you get exact match in your inference
and training engine.
There are also things related to chat
template fixing where token in token out
makes sure that your multi-turn agentic
chat templates will be all aligned and
then the all the tokens will be matching
the pri prior tokens prior turns tokens
without any train inference mismatch as
well. And third thing is related to
algam fix. There have been uh draw out
routing replay and also truncated mass
important sampling. Those are all
techniques to enable stable training
with large scale for reinforcement
learning stage
and force is also um more more uh
engineering driven. It's mostly we have
da support for most of models and they
are all verified with our own training
roles where whenever we support new
models like inkling like Kim K3 training
we always have have our own in-house
training run to make sure the K is
controlled the reward goes up so that
people uh can use the framework directly
without any concert.
Okay. So lastly uh for high school like
Asha and the mouse are also like keeping
improving around that. Um we basically
have much um sophisticated and like
mature support for fully async RL which
get to compare with synchronous case. Um
basically we get to uh overlap the time
for roll out and train and also disc
disagregate those two settings to make
sure um those are um making best use of
your GPU and also we have very heavy
investment in low precision training
where your rollout will be in a lower
precision and your training back end
will be with um uh some type of like
quantization training. So that enables
us to train with lower precision in
robot stage where we natively support
like 8 bit and also four-bit training
and in this case we also recently work
with humans end to support MVIP4 native
rowout in R stage without any
performance lose.
Okay. Uh as a summary uh we are
producing and working on a mouse and
then we welcome everyone to uh
contribute work with us and try that
provide feedback. So uh please also take
a look at both projects and then we love
to hear more from you. Thank you.
All righty. Thank you Banga. Next up we
have uh let's see Runja Singha with IBM.
So,
>> so you're using your laptop. We have
your slides.
>> Yeah, that's fine. I use my slides.
>> And so this is
>> Okay, there you go.
>> And this is I press this.
>> So that's advanced and that's back.
>> Okay, perfect.
>> Okay. Well, hi everyone. So when agents
speak in different languages,
you need to write custom code, glue code
adapters, and that doesn't really scale
too well.
So, and that's really the tower of Babel
problem. So, Nlip is the universal
handshake
that makes seamless interoperability
real.
So if the agent speaks NLIP, it speaks
to everything else that does. So think
of NLP as the HTTP of intent
and it follows a very similar approach
of being minimal and neutral.
So HTTP is a neutral uniform way to
transfer resources between heterogenous
clients and servers. And enl is a
neutral uniform way to transfer meaning
or intent between heterogenous agents
and clients.
So it came out of a working group of
academia and um industry researchers and
practitioners and it was sponsored by
the enterprise neurosystems group and
the AI alliance and it is now a ECMA
standard and TC56 is the technical
committee that drove uh NLP and
JavaScript was also standardized by the
ECMA uh body and some of the contri and
the contribution organizations are on
the right hand side.
Now the AI based software systems or
agents are being deployed in a wide
range of applications.
So agents serve different
functionalities and operated by
different organizations. They must
interoperate through a common
communication protocol. So if let's look
at the left diagram. So a traditional
protocol. So agent one speaks language
A, agent two speaks language B and what
passes over the wire is language P. Now
in a traditional protocol they all have
to be the same. A is equal to P is equal
to B and if there is any change in the
schema or change in fields it typically
breaks and that's really the hard-coded
integrations and that is tight coupling
and that creates issues with
interoperability version management and
if you look at the right hand side
that's the domain that's where comes
into the picture where you have agent
one that speaks language Agent two
speaks language B and what passes over
the wire is P and A doesn't have to be
equal to B doesn't have to be equal to
P. So it promotes flexibility but the
condition is that there needs to be
intelligence at both endpoints so it can
translate between these messages
and given the current trends you'd
expect intelligence to be available in
solutions and systems um and it
continually improves.
So, Enley provides a very simple open
common standard protocol for
applications, agents and services to
communicate with each other.
It assumes intelligence at both
endpoints to enable the semantic
understanding and it follows the request
and response paradigm to ensure that the
meaning or intent is refined and
confirmed before the agent gets to act
on it. And if a m and if a message is
ambiguous it will um the agent does
doesn't just fail it will ask for
clarifications. So that's really the
request response paradigm and it is
built for enterprise reality. So if you
deploy an enterprise or otherwise some
serious application some of the
requirements for the protocol are on the
right hand side. It needs to be secure
got to have safeguards. Um it's
transport agnostic and um and
essentially uses the existing
infrastructure. you don't it's not
rebuilding the wheel. Suppose multimedia
communication is efficient. I have some
charts to show that um it's it's can be
implemented multiple languages and it is
an open standard uh governed by ECMA and
we've also um submitted that for the ISO
um standardization and um
so that's currently in progress.
Great. So now coming to the Nlip uh
specific uh specifications, it is
deliberately minimal. So if you see the
message model, it's a lightweight JSON.
It is just five fields and out of these
five fields, three are mandatory. So you
have the content which essentially is a
lightweight JSON um envelope which
contains the information that is
exchanged. Um the format is u you
specify is it text is it structured is
it binary and then your sub format is
essentially a refinement if it's text
what language that text is in and
encoding for a binary uh content and
then there are two optional um um fields
that suggest a parsing hint and you can
have more additional content in in the
sub message but that's really it in the
core and data these five fields and if
you compare with some of the uh more um
popular um protocols that's used let's
say A2A or MCP you're looking at 60 to
99 to the full data model having 166 to
480 fields so in that sense it's very
lightweight and in terms of it's very
simple to implement over standard um
transports so you have the bindings for
HTTP for um uh websocket for AMQP and
these are specified um in the ECMA uh
specifications and you can access that
from um the GitHub page and it is secure
by design so it's mandatory. So you have
three profiles from basic to um rigorous
enterprise profiles and addresses
various uh AI specific risks besides
just the transport security.
Now LIP can interoperate with various
single vendor protocols in two modes.
The first mode is LIP is a northbound
API and single vendor protocol a
southbound API and you use the
translation agent and LM pod to
translate between these two. And in mode
B um if um it can interoperate across
multiple domains and each of these
domains you can have multiple agents
that speaks in their own language using
different agent frameworks. But as long
as they um are NLIP aware they can all
communicate with each other. And so this
is a very powerful um uh feature.
Now several proof of concept
applications have been developed by um
companies and universities and across
multiple domains. You have telecom to
shopping to sustainability to multimodal
customer support and so on. And a lot of
these are also available on um the
project page. So I'll dive a bit deeper
into the customer support
where in this case a customer uh submits
a voice request. That's a query that is
then it's an audio that's then um
converted to text using a speechtoext
model um NVIDIA ASR that is then we then
um um um use enlip over HTTP and send
that information to the channel
recommener which picks up the most
relevant subreddit channels uh for that
query. uh that's then sent using nlip um
um over HTTP to the search agent that
picks up the most relevant topics from
those channels, ranks them and sends it
back to the customer. Essentially, a
customer query picks up the most
relevant topics from Reddit and and the
customer gets those responses. So we
compare NLP with A2A uh for this
workflow and
we use a very similar symmetric
um identical timing harness for NLP and
A2A and we use three variants of A2A and
we also have phase level instrumentation
that's message creation connection and
send to really understand where timing
is going and the total latency is really
a summation of these three phases and we
use two machines um two data sets
containing several uh customer queries
and so the average total latency across
the queries on both the phases where we
use NLP you'll see the Nlip is in blue
and then you have variants of the A28
SDK to a cache optimized A28 to a
lightweight Python A2A on the the right
hand side and you'll find that it's the
the minimal nature of um A2A is
displayed here. Of course, is I would
say it's preliminary experiments. You
can do a lot more complex um uh
workflows and experiments and that's
something that we like to do and if
you'd like to participate that'll be
terrific as well. Uh but it gives you a
sense as to it's a very lightweight um
message envelope.
Now for practitioners,
it will boil down to when do we use
these protocols. So you can choose NLP
when you're looking at when you have a
use case that is around um requires
heterogenous protocol interoperability
or semantic flexibility or cross
protocol mediation um and choose HA when
you have governance and audit needs or
task ccentric or longunning workflows
strict schema enforcement uh
deterministic execution and you can even
choose a hybrid when you have mixed
workloads um and end up at the
coordination layer um and then A2A at
the govern These are various guidance
that we are working on based upon our
experiments and evaluation. But the
important uh thing here is that the
protocol selection should be guided by
the workload characteristics. Currently
we have several protocols essentially
long tailor protocols. You have
domaincentric protocols being introduced
for payments and shopping and so on. So
how do we work across these protocols
and communicate in an interable manner
and that's where the NLP fits in.
So to summarize, it's essentially it's a
standardbased semantic protocol that
connects clients to agents and bridges
different agent protocols. It's simple,
it's open, it's lightweight, it's
neutral and think of it as the HTTP of
intent and it is built for the
intelligence error. And um in
preliminary experiments we observed that
it was efficient during message creation
and transport. And for practitioners um
you can choose an based upon agent
workload characteristics.
Now you'll find the details of enlip on
the project page. Um it has been
integrated with ag2 framework as well
that's downloaded tens of thousands of
times daily probably a million in a
month. Um so if you're interested in um
your feedback of course we always
welcome that it's a very active
committee we meet weekly and continue to
uh develop this um uh protocol and uh if
you have any use cases in mind uh
participate in evaluation or contribute
to ENLP we'd love to hear from you on
that. So there are emails and other
contact details on the project page. So
with that thank you very much.
[applause]
All right, thank you Ron John. That's it
for Atlas stage today. So, thank you
everyone. There's reception and poster
presentations on the first floor if you
want to check those out. And then
tomorrow we have a bunch of new talks
and enterprise AI um agent evaluation
and benchmarks as well as AI for math.
So see everyone tomorrow feel free to
walk to Zelerbach other places or go to
the first floor. Thank you.